<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A summary of the Bible vvherein the generall heads of the seuerall bookes thereof are so methodically set downe, as may be a helpe to the vnskilfull reader / by Robert Bruen ...</title>
            <author>Bruen, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 143 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11815</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20025006</idno>
  <idno type="VID">178475</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240906899</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 3930.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S1062</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11815)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1725:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A summary of the Bible vvherein the generall heads of the seuerall bookes thereof are so methodically set downe, as may be a helpe to the vnskilfull reader / by Robert Bruen ...</title>
                  <author>Bruen, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 267 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.P. for John Budge, and are to be sold at his shop, at the Greene Dragon in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L¹² M¹¹.</note>
                  <note>Pages 242 and 243 misnumbered as 240 and 241 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178475:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178475:1"/>
            <p>A SVMMARY OF THE BIBLE: VVherein the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heads of the seuerall Bookes thereof are so <hi>metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically set downe, as may be a helpe to the vnskilfull Reader.</hi> By <hi>Robert Bruen,</hi> Minister of Gods <hi>Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Reuel. 1. 3.</bibl> Blessed is he that readeth, and they that heare the words of this Prophesie, and keepe those things that are written therein.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>John Budge,</hi> and are to be sold at his shop, at the Greene Dragon in Pauls Church-yard. 1623.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:178475:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:178475:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, and most vertuous Lady, the Lady <hi>Lucy</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesse of <hi>Bedford.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: At what time the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, an outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentation of GODS presence among his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient people of <hi>Israel,</hi> was erected in the wildernes,
<pb facs="tcp:178475:3"/> euery hand was busied and heart addicted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it. And so great was the zeale of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of that time therein that <hi>Moses</hi> was moued to bid them forbeare to bring any more offerings ere they would desist. As was then the Tabernacle, so is the Word of God vnto vs now. Happines or misery befalleth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where it is planted or wanting. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery one of an abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity should be ymployed one way or other to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the welfare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, either by learned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions
<pb facs="tcp:178475:3"/> of the more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and mystical parts, or in familiar manner set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe, for the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the weaker sort, such things therein as concerne faith and good life; or by painfull and powerfull preaching so carue the Word, as euery soule that commeth with hungry and prepared af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, may haue it por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And happy he that either so teaching it, or taught by it, is found walking in the light and rule thereof; and shall be sure to heare Christ pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce vnto him in the
<pb facs="tcp:178475:4"/> great day of Retributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Well done, good ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and faithfull.</hi> And therefore although the argument of this little booke (great for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) had deserued a farre better and more skilfull Pen-man thenmy selfe: Yet as one who desireth the general benefit of all, and vnwilling that any <hi>vacuum</hi> should be in that remainder of time which God shall giue; I haue endeauoured (though in much weakenesse) to set downe the briefe of such things, as are at large scattered and diffused
<pb facs="tcp:178475:4"/> through-out the body of the sacred Scriptures. A worke which (if effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and elaborately per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) would bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the view and reuiew of all such as desired to reade the SCRIPTVRE with profit, and would profit by reading. And because when wee haue done the best wee can, yet detraction will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the penne, euen as the Crowes doe the sower, or the Fowles that fell vpon <hi>Abrahams</hi> sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; in which regard, as there is need of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage to shelter writing
<pb facs="tcp:178475:5"/> from Calumny: So for my owne part, I haue humbly submitted these my poore and weake en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors, vnder the wings of your Ladiships <hi>Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble protection,</hi> partly out of my opinion, That the fruits of the Gospell should first bee offered to such (your Ladiship a principall one) as are the Patrons or patronesses of the Gospell. And se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in lieu of my true and vnfained affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in remembrance of that Honorable Saint now with GOD, in her life time the subiect of
<pb facs="tcp:178475:5"/> many excellencies, and patterne of true Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, namely, your Lady mother: By whose boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie I haue fared the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: So not knowing whither to direct my thoughts better, then by way of thankfulnesse, I haue reflected them vpon your Ladiship, as the proper obiect, and heire of her possessions &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. If your Ladiship shall please to accept these my small endeuors in good worth, I haue my desire, and shall day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray the Lord to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish your Noble heart
<pb facs="tcp:178475:6"/> more and more in the truth of that profession, which maketh you graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with God, and those that truely loue &amp; feare him. From my house at <hi>West Markham,</hi> the fift of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in the Lord, euer to bee commanded, <hi>ROBERT BRVEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:178475:6"/>
            <head>To the Christian <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, thou hast here in a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row roome set before thee some helpes (as I conceiue) for thy better and more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie vnderstanding in some poynts, the Contents of the sacred Bible. It is the Booke of bookes, and so sweete to all that conceiue the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:178475:7"/> of godlines, that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> is said to eate it. And <hi>Dauid</hi> a King, to prize it aboue al riches, and to spend the day and night in the meditation of it. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> professeth himselfe to estimate it, and the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his course therein a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his life. Here is the wel from whence the waters of life doe plenteously flow: which who so drinketh shal neuer be more athirst. Here he that is spiritually sicke, may be recouered, according to the power of God that worketh thereby: here the simple may haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing aboue the learned
<pb facs="tcp:178475:7"/> Scribe, &amp; such as by a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular proprietie, may make him wise vnto saluation. The treasure thē being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and knowne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to consist, the next thing worthy of our search, should bee how to attaine it; to which we should endeuour, as we do in matters of farre lesse importance. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pēter hath his Rule, the Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sitian his preparatiues. In Arts there are bookes dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue for the attainment of them. And therefore as we commonly lanch forth into the main Ocean, beginning at the Riuers that run ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: And Children are
<pb facs="tcp:178475:8"/> led by the hand, before they get the vse of their feete: Euen so, although the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, by which the Scriptures were written, be the inward and Master-teacher, yet as oftentimes we take the benefit of the staffe to walke with, to helpe the body; so is it in the study of good things, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod being as the mindes-waggoner, and that order best, when by generall heads (as markes in the way) we may bee kept the better from erring. Which thing is the ayme of this small ensuing tract, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Reader may see in a
<pb facs="tcp:178475:8"/> generall manner, what eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry seuerall Booke of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture principally intendeth, set downe in methodical manner, for the more easie vnderstanding and better retaining of the same in the Readers me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <p>And although all Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be giuen by inspiration from God, and euery part of it be of vse for the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly building: yet as some roomes are of different sort in the materiall edifice, so is it in the sacred Story, wherein some parcels are recommended vnto vs, not onely as excellent in
<pb facs="tcp:178475:9"/> themselues; but as seruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and keyes to vnlocke other places of Scriptures, and make them more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar to the godly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposed Reader. Such as are the Bookes of <hi>MOSES,</hi> to all those that come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the Bookes of <hi>Samuel,</hi> to the Psalmes of <hi>DAVID;</hi> those of the <hi>Kings,</hi> to the <hi>Prophets:</hi> The Acts of the Apostles, to their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles. And according to this direction I haue been purposely more prolix and large in setting downe some things in all or most of the forenamed Bookes. As concerning the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
<pb facs="tcp:178475:9"/> parts of euery Chapter, (although in some places I haue not been wanting that way) because the same in sundry learned Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of some, &amp; abbreuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of others is set down, I haue forborne to labour therein. If thou hast better helpes in this kind, in the feare of GOD vse them to the improuement of sauing knowledge. If these of mine may any thing auaile thee, here thou hast them before thee: And the Lord blesse them vnto thee, and thee vnto himselfe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in, and for</hi> the Lord, <hi>ROBERT BRVEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:178475:10"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biblical_epitome">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:178475:10"/>
            <head>A SVMMARY <hi>of the</hi> BIBLE.</head>
            <div n="old" type="testament">
               <div n="Genesis" type="book">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGH GOD, who is goodnesse and fulnesse it selfe, nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to create any thing, yet hath vouchsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to make man, and out of the masse of mankind
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178475:11"/> reserued a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto himselfe, called the Church.</p>
                  <p>The Church is but one, though consisting of many members, and in diuers times and places of the world produced and made visible, euen as the water running tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row many Countries, is but one Sea in respect of the Element, but hath diuers appellations ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the places it passeth by.</p>
                  <p>The Church of God is considerable according to the institution and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thereof, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:178475:11"/> of it so ordered.</p>
                  <p>The Institution of the Church consisteth in it framing and inspiring.</p>
                  <p>In respect of the frame, it is called a Body; <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. 4. of which Christ is the head, and the Word the immortal seed wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is begotten.</p>
                  <p>The inspiring of it, is by the Spirit which crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the instrument of faith, and knitteth the beleeuer inseparably to Christ.</p>
                  <p>The operation of it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in seuerall instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces shewed heereafter in the Children of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178475:12"/> Church in the seuerall ages of the world.</p>
                  <p>The Ages of the world are in number eight, in the account of some.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="age_of_the_world">
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The first Age.</note> The first age is recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> containing yeeres, 1656. and the History thereof is set down from the first Chapter of <hi>Genesis</hi> to the seuenth, wherein are to be considered of persons and actions by them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
                     <p>The persons are consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered generally or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly.</p>
                     <p>Of the first, are all the Patriarkes or chiefe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178475:12"/> that were before the Flood, as <hi>Adam, Sheth, Enosh, Kenan, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halaleel, Iered, Henoch, Methuselah, Lamech,</hi> &amp; <hi>Noah.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The persons among these of especiall note for the building of the Church of God were:</p>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>Adam,</hi> as the roote of the Church.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 <hi>Habel,</hi> the first fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the Church, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesis</hi> 4.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 <hi>Sheth,</hi> the third son of <hi>Adam,</hi> the second per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for building of the Church in <hi>Abels</hi> roome.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>Henoch,</hi> the first fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178475:13"/> of the Church ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp body and soule into heauen, the sonne of <hi>Iared,</hi> chap. 5. 18. and not of <hi>Cain,</hi> chap. 4. 17.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 <hi>Noah,</hi> the second fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued in the Arke.</p>
                     <p>So that although Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on decayed in the dayes of <hi>Enosh,</hi> yet God would not haue his Church vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ruined: without which the world would not stand; and therefore Christ descended as well of the Fathers before the flood, as of those that came after.</p>
                     <p>The persons thus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178475:13"/> the Religious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or operations doe follow by them perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; shewed, 1. in their Inuocation of GODS Name, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. 26. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by sacrificing vnto GOD, which is knowne to bee a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous act, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 15. and by Gods acceptation of the thing done, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. <hi>Verse</hi> 20.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="age_of_the_world">
                     <head>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>The</hi> 2. <hi>Age.</hi>
                        </note> The Second Age follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from <hi>Noah</hi> to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> containing y. 363. &amp; 10. d. in the Patriarches after the Flood, which were, <hi>Shē,</hi>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:178475:14"/>
                        <hi>Arpachshad, Shelah, Eber, Peleg, Reu, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rug, Nahor, Terah</hi> &amp; <hi>Abraham:</hi> set downe from the 6. of <hi>Genesis,</hi> to the 12. Chapter.</head>
                     <p>CONCERNING these persons, little is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued of great note, saue of <hi>Sem,</hi> the second sonne of <hi>Noah,</hi> in whose Line the true Church remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and <hi>Abraham,</hi> but rather, of the sinnes of those times, and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments accordingly.</p>
                     <p>The sinnes by them committed, were either before the Flood, as of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178475:14"/> Crueltie and prophane marriages, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. for which God brought the Deluge, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. or after the Flood.</p>
                     <p>The sinnes most no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after the Flood, were of <hi>Noah</hi> sinning of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and of <hi>Cham,</hi> his yongest sonne mocking his Father, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. so that as before the Flood, <hi>Cains</hi> posteritie was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by name, <hi>The Sonnes of men,</hi> sauouring more of them then of God; so after the Flood, <hi>Cham,</hi> of <hi>Cain,</hi> was the first Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Irreligion.</p>
                     <p>The punishment of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178475:15"/>
                        <hi>Cham,</hi> is noted in a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Seede, and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Church, which should afterward molest the people of God, <hi>Cha.</hi> 10. <hi>verse</hi> 6. to 21. and the effects that succeeded in the world; namely, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of Monarchie, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. and confusion of Languages, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>verse</hi> 7, 8, 9.</p>
                     <p>Languages are consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, either in the vse or abuse of them.</p>
                     <p>Their vse, by obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing what they were at first; the abuse, as they became afterwards.</p>
                     <p>The World at first was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:178475:15"/> all of one Language, but afterwards was diuided into many; some thinke, 72. but the Hebrew was preserued in the Familie of <hi>Heber</hi> the sonne of <hi>Shelah, Chap.</hi> 11. 14. of whom came the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes.</p>
                     <p>The vse of Languages aright considered, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in respect of the Teacher or Learner.</p>
                     <p>The Teacher best in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structeth by his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Tongues, in which the 2. Testaments were written, the old in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> the new in <hi>Greek</hi> the Mother-tongue,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178475:16"/> to a great part of the world, spred ouer the same by <hi>Alexanders</hi> Conquest: which bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing befell in <hi>Iaphets</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie, for couering his Fathers nakednesse.</p>
                     <p>The Learner is best taught in the language hee best vnderstandeth, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. So that the gifts of tongues are now necessary to deale with all persons in their owne languages, holding in the diuersity of tongues the vnity of faith. And that as many were diuided by the multiplying of tongues, so now by the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178475:16"/> gift thereof many by Christ are vnited into one body.</p>
                     <p>The abuse of langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges followeth, and that principally by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists, in a twofold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 In that of long time they were carelesse of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny translation, teaching that ignorance was the mother of deuotion.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. When they were ashamed of that position they dimmed the Word with a barbarous transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Latine; which vulgar translation was made so authenticall by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178475:17"/> the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> that none might presume to reiect it. Whereas there was no Latine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in <hi>England,</hi> within the first 600. yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter CHRIST.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="age_of_the_world">
                     <head>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>The</hi> 3. <hi>Age.</hi>
                        </note> The third Age followeth, containing yeeres 430. from the departure of <hi>Abraham</hi> from <hi>Vr</hi> in <hi>Caldea,</hi> vnto the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of Israel from <hi>Aegypt,</hi> set downe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. to 14. of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HEre wee are to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the famous
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:178475:17"/> Patriarches to whom GOD made promises; and these persons are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther generally, or more particularly to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the faithull, to whom the promise was first made, from the 11. Chapter of <hi>Genesis</hi> to the 25. Chapter.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Of <hi>Isaac,</hi> in whom the promise was made, Chapter 25. to 28. saue of his age, and death, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chapter 35. vers. 28, 29.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, Of <hi>Iacob,</hi> of whose seede consisted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178475:18"/> the greatest visibility of the Church both for multitude and potencie of <hi>Iewes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentiles</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the faith that came of him: the histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of him from his birth to the history of <hi>Ioseph,</hi> from Chapter 25. to 37.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 Of <hi>Ioseph,</hi> from chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 37. to 49. and from thence to the end of the booke, of <hi>Iacobs</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
                     <p>The particular consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of these follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of Gods proceeding to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and that by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178475:18"/> obseruing both the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises made to him of God, the time when, and the confirmation of the things promised.</p>
                     <p>The promises were concerning persons and possessions.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Of a blessed seede in <hi>Isaack</hi> by <hi>Sarah,</hi> of whom came al the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Rom.</hi> 4. 6. or of outward greatnes, and multitude in the posterity of <hi>Ismael</hi> of <hi>Hagar</hi> an Egyptian Woman, Chapter 25. vers. 12. to 19. and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise of his posterity by <hi>Keturah,</hi> of whom came
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:178475:19"/> the <hi>Midianites,</hi> and the <hi>Persian Magi,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 The time that these promises were made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. 1. either iust before that <hi>Lot</hi> and hee were seuered, Chapter 12. Secondly, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally after their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, Chapter 13. vers. 14, 15. That nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lot</hi> nor his posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty should make claime to any of the promises, which God had made in peculiar to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 The possession pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, was <hi>Canaā,</hi> which was assured to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Chapter 12. 7. and 17.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178475:19"/> 4, 8. And to <hi>Isaak,</hi> chap. 26. 4. and to <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his seede, Chap. 28. 13.</p>
                     <p>The confirmation fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth of the things promised, and that first, by exchange of Name from <hi>Abram</hi> a man worldly eminent, to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> a Father of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, yea, of all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Secondly, by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of Circumcision; wherein the distinction of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. Thirdly, by visible signe of a heifer diuided, Chapter 15.</p>
                     <p>Concerning <hi>Isaak,</hi> we <note place="margin">Isaac.</note> are to obserue somewhat
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:178475:20"/> touching the breuitie vsed by <hi>Moses</hi> in pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the history, and of the history it selfe.</p>
                     <p>The breuity thereof in a twofold respect; 1. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the visibility of the Church was most in <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Iacob</hi> had more troubles then his Father, and therefore had need to be more large in setting them downe.</p>
                     <p>The history it selfe, in respect of his troubles or infirmities: his troubles either personall, as to be scoffed by <hi>Ismael,</hi> Chap. 21. to bee sacrificed in Mount <hi>Moriah,</hi> Chap.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:178475:20"/> 22. to bee childlesse 20. yeeres after he was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, Chap. 25. To so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne into <hi>Gerar,</hi> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough famine, and there his life to be indangered through his wife, Chap. 26. 2. reall, as to haue his wels stopped.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 His infirmities, first to lye to saue his life; Chap. 26. Secondly his desire to blesse <hi>Esau</hi> whō the LORD would not choose, and who would haue sold it as he did his birth-right, or haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned it, and so haue brought a curse vpon the world; in which regard,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:178475:21"/> it was a speciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God that <hi>Isaac</hi> wanted the sence of see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Chap. 27.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Iacob,</hi> the Church <note place="margin">Iacob.</note> is cleerly represented, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the visibility of it, or in the troubles that befall it.</p>
                     <p>The visibilitie of the Church set foorth in <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> is in the exchange of his name, and number of his troubles.</p>
                     <p>His name was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from <hi>Iacob</hi> his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall name, as Father of a familie, to <hi>Israel,</hi> which was giuen him by grace, Chap. 32. 28. and 35. 10.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:178475:21"/> Secondly, his Children were eitherby his wiues, or his wiues seruants.</p>
                     <p>His wiues were <hi>Leah,</hi> and <hi>Rachel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By <hi>Leah</hi> he had <hi>Ruben, Simeon, Leui, Iudah,</hi> Chap. 29. <hi>Issachar, Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulon,</hi> and <hi>Dinah,</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 30.</p>
                     <p>By <hi>Rachel</hi> he had <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph,</hi> Chap. 30. and <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin,</hi> Chap. 35.</p>
                     <p>By <hi>Billah Rachels</hi> maid he had <hi>Dan,</hi> Chapter 30. vers. 6. and <hi>Napthalie,</hi> vers. 8.</p>
                     <p>By <hi>Zilpah Leahs</hi> maid he had <hi>Gad,</hi> vers. 11. and <hi>Asher,</hi> vers. 13. And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:178475:22"/> of these came the twelue Tribes which were,</p>
                     <q>Ruben, Simeon, Iudah, Issachar, Zebulun, Dan, Gad, Asher, Nepthali, Beniamin, Ephraim, <hi>&amp;</hi> Manasses.</q>
                     <p>So that of <hi>Iacobs</hi> Sons of whom were the Tribes, some were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and others inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The persons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, were either in this place, namely, <hi>Leui,</hi> and <hi>Ioseph; Leui</hi> for his crueltie, and <hi>Ioseph</hi> for his double portion: and the persons inserted in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:178475:22"/> their roome, were <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> and <hi>Manasses.</hi> Secondly, or in other places of Scripture, and so <hi>Simeon</hi> is left out by <hi>Moses</hi> in numbring the Tribes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. because hee was without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and <hi>Dan</hi> by Saint <hi>Iohn, Reuel.</hi> 7. 7. because that Tribe caused the first Idolatry when the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> came into the land of <hi>Canaan, Iudg.</hi> 18. 30. Whence also wee may conclude the Booke of <hi>Iudith</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrypha, because she is said to come of that Tribe, which in <hi>Iacobs</hi>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:178475:23"/> Will hath a curse: and yet <hi>Leui</hi> is inserted in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> because that of <hi>Israel,</hi> in relation to CHRIST, were made Priests vnto God.</p>
                     <p>The representation of the Churches troubles in <hi>Iacob</hi> doth follow.</p>
                     <p>The troubles of <hi>Iacob</hi> were in his Iourneyes:</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Into <hi>Mesopotamia</hi> to serue his vnkle <hi>Laban,</hi> where he had his wiues, Chap. 29. and his riches, Chap. 30.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Into <hi>Canaan,</hi> where he was troubled with his brother <hi>Esau,</hi> Chap. 32. and 33. and in his owne
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:178475:23"/> children during his life, Chapters 37, 38, 42.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Into <hi>Egypt,</hi> where of the troubles befalling his posterity after his death, with the cause thereof, namely, the sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Ioseph</hi> to the <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maelites,</hi> Chap. 37. 28.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Ioseph,</hi> consider his <note place="margin">Joseph.</note> occultation in <hi>Egipt,</hi> and manifestation.</p>
                     <p>His occultation, for the space of 22. yeeres before hee was made knowne.</p>
                     <p>His manifestation, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in respect of <hi>Iacob,</hi> or of God.</p>
                     <p>Of <hi>Iacob,</hi> his necessity
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:178475:24"/> vrging him to send into <hi>Egypt</hi> twice to buy corn, Chap. 42. 2. and 43. 2.</p>
                     <p>Of God, the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his prouidence to prouide for <hi>Iacob</hi> and his familie, Chapter 45. 7, 8. and for discouery of their sin against their brother, Chap. 42. 21, 22. And lastly, to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest <hi>Ioseph</hi> a liuely type of Christ, sold of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and afterwards aduanced: and setteth foorth the estate of the Church in it depression in this world by afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and exaltation by glory, sometime in this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:178475:24"/> life, but most assuredly in the Life to come.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Exodus" type="book">
                  <head>EXODVS.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Hitherto of the Church in the dayes of the Patriarkes: now of it, they being dead, and she left in Egipt, the house of Bōdage.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>WHere we haue to consider of their inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the meanes thereof.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:178475:25"/>
                  <p n="1"> 1 Their inlargement noted in the different number of the <hi>Israelites</hi> at their going out into <hi>Egypt,</hi> namely, but 70. and at their going forth, sixe hundred thousand, beside Children, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 37.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the meanes, &amp; manner of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out, are personally and instrumentally to be considered.</p>
                  <p>The persons or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners for that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice principally appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, were two brethren, <hi>Moses</hi> (the Pen-man of these 5. Bookes) and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:178475:25"/>
                     <hi>Aaron</hi> the sons of two Leuites, <hi>Amram,</hi> and <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabed,</hi> Chap. 2. and 6. Their commission was to let <hi>Pharaoh</hi> know what God would haue him doe, namely, to let his people goe out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> with their substance two dayes iourney into the wildernesse to serue him, Chapters 3. and 8. or what to suffer for not doing it.</p>
                  <p>The instrument or signe that was appointed for the effecting of Gods iudgement herein, was by a rod, sometime in the hand of <hi>Moses,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178475:26"/> in the hand of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> Chapter 7. vers. 9, 10, 19, 20. and 10. vers. 3, 13, 21, 22. and 8. 5, 16. but principally in <hi>Aarons</hi> hand, being the minister of the iudgement.</p>
                  <p>The Commission be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing shewed, the effects and issue doe follow, and they are either partiall or finall.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Partiall, of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters turned into blood, Chap. 7. 22. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> promised to let them goe at the second plague of the frogges, Chap. 8. 22. promised absolutely at the thunder and haile,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:178475:26"/> Chap. 9. 28. at the gras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers confesseth his sinne, Chap. 10. vers. 16, 17. At the darknesse all should goe but sheepe &amp; cattell, verse 24. at the tenth plague, to wit, the death of the first borne all must goe, and were thrust out, Chap. 12. 31, 32, 33.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The totall &amp; finall iudgement followeth, where consider, the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> that parted with their Iewels, Chap. 11. of God, who in iustice ouerthrewe them in the Sea, Chap. 14. Of the Israelites in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:178475:27"/> their thanksgiuing for their deliuerance, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 15.</p>
                  <div n="4" type="age_of_the_world">
                     <head>The fourth Age followeth.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>Hitherto of the Church in <hi>Egypt:</hi> now of it in the <note place="margin">
                              <hi>The</hi> 4. <hi>Age.</hi>
                           </note> Wildernesse, and of the fourth Age, from the departure of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Israel</hi> foorth of <hi>Egypt,</hi> till the first building of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, containing yeeres 480. The History whereof is from this place, to the latter end of the first booke of the Kings.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:178475:27"/>
                     <p>IN the narration of the people of <hi>Israel</hi> in the wildernesse, their nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishment there, and nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is to be considered, in respect of their bodies and soules.</p>
                     <p>For their bodies, God in miraculous manner prouided <hi>Manna</hi> for their bread, Quailes for their meate, Chap. 16. &amp; water by striking a rock, Chap. 17.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Their nurture by the benefite of good Lawes; and they either Morall &amp; eternal, which God pronounced with his owne mouth, giuen
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:178475:28"/> the 50<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. day after their going out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten first in the hearts of our first Parents, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in stone, Chap. 20. seruing to explaine the law of nature.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Ceremoniall, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31. for the outward seruice of GOD, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to that people: all which rites had respect to the heart and mind, whereby God would be worshipped, <hi>Esay</hi> 58. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 12. and they ended in Christ. 3. Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallr, especting ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, Chapters, 21,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:178475:28"/> 22, 23, to vphold a right performance of the two former, by inflicting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments on the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressors: and both the Ceremoniall and Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all lawes were written by <hi>Moses.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hitherto concerning the Lawes: now followeth to shew what <hi>MOSES</hi> was commaunded to make.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>THE things so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, were nine: The Tabernacle, Arke, Mercy-seate, Table of shew-bread, Candlestick,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:178475:29"/> Chapters 25. 27. Altar of burnt-offering. Chap. 27. 1. Altar for perfume, Chap. 30. 1. Brazen La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Chap. 38. and the Priests garments, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 39.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 The Tabernacle or Tents were certaine moueable Habitations, appointed by GOD in the wildernesse; That as great persons haue faire houses for their reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; so God the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle for his worship, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his people must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort to him, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 17. 4, 5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 5, 6.</p>
                     <p>In this, the matter, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:178475:29"/> and approbation of it, erected, is considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                     <p>The matter was of such things as the people had &amp; freely offered. 2. The mystery was to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Gods presence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his people, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant to them made, <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 44. in vse till the Temple was erected, and then it was set there with the Arke and holy vessels, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8. 6. Secondly to set forth the Church militant, and the flitting estate thereof, <hi>Psal.</hi> 15. 1. as the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did the Church try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:178475:30"/> Thirdly, the approbation of it, and that was by God, after it was erected, and all things performed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, Chap. 40.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 The Arke was the principall part of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, which was in the most holy place of al wherein were put the Tables of stone; and a certaine place for the <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> where to offer their sacrifices: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they might offer, 1. before the Arke seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the Tabernacle 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 15, 17. 2. or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:178475:30"/> before the Tabernacle when the Ark was away, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 17. 3. and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily in other places by Diuine dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, as did <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 9. and <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 25. and <hi>Elias,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18. yet princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally they sacrificed when the Tabernacle &amp; Arke were both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 <hi>Mercy-seate,</hi> as Gods place of audience, from which the Lord spake vnto <hi>Moses, Numb.</hi> 7. 89.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 <hi>Table of Shrew bread,</hi> which for the matter was of <hi>Shittim,</hi> and dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:178475:31"/> wood, couered ouer with pure gold, whereon was set face bread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereof the Priests onely might eate.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 <hi>Candlesticke,</hi> which was set in the holy place of the Sanctuary, whose lampes were dayly dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and oyle supplyed by <hi>Aaron,</hi> or by his sonnes the Priests at his appointment.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 <hi>Altar of burnt-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring,</hi> which was but one made of brasse, and set in the Court of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary onely, hauing a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen grate; whereon the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:178475:31"/> fire was put for sacrifice.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 <hi>Altar for perfume,</hi> of Shittim wood ouerlayd with gold, whereupon onely the incense was to be offred, which was made of diuers spices beaten, and afterwards offered vp by the Priest in the holy place.</p>
                     <p n="8">8 <hi>Brazen Lauer,</hi> which was for the priests to wash their hands and feete when they mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred before the Lord, and entred into the holy place, in their cleane gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                     <p n="9">9 <hi>The Priests gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> both for <hi>Aaron</hi>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:178475:32"/> and his sons, Chap. 39. <hi>Aarons</hi> most remarkable garments were the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. 12, 21. The brest-plate of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vers. 15, 22. <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> vers. 30. and a plate on his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, wherein was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen, <hi>Holinesse to the Lord,</hi> vers. 36.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Leviticus" type="book">
                  <head>LEVITICVS.</head>
                  <p>THE manner of performing reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious seruice fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, wherein of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:178475:32"/> Commander, or things commanded.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The Commander is God, who in this book commādeth such things as were done in the first moneth of the second yeere after their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming foorth of <hi>Egypt,</hi> at <hi>Mount Sinai.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is touching actions and actors.</p>
                  <p>Actions are such sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices as were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lord to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> wherein the seuerall sorts, matter and myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them is seuerally to be considered.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:178475:33"/>
                  <p>The sorts of sacrifices were either,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Burnt offrings, cha. 1. so called, because all was offered and consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med therein by fire that came from God; the skin onely was the Priests.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Meate offerings, Chap. 2. for acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement that they did hold their meat and food of God: and because part therof went as meat vnto the Priest who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Peace offerings, Chap. 3. whereof one part was burnt, the other was the Priests, and the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:178475:33"/> third part the offerers, &amp; this was also called the sacrifice of prayse, or free-will offering for the obtainment of any bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, Chap. 7.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Sin-offering, Chap. 4. for Ignorance, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Priest, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, Prince, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate person, with the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall oblations for each.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Trespasse offering, Chap. 5. for things done amisse, and afterward knowne and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
                  <p>The matter of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices followeth.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:178475:34"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Of things hauing life, Chap. 1.</item>
                     <item>2 Of things without life, Chap. 2.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The mystery of these Sacrifices.</p>
                  <p>1 To note our pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that wee like beasts had deserued to dye. 2. To assure vs of the remission of our sins in Christs death, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Sacrifices, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the aboundance of grace redounding vnto vs by the Sacrifice of Christ.</p>
                  <p>The persons sacrificing doe follow, and they were either publike or
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:178475:34"/> priuate. Publike, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 8, 9, 10. Priuate, from the 11. to the end.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Publike and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, and so was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Aaron</hi> the high Priest.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Ordinary, and so all the Priests of the Tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> whereof there were great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the <hi>Iewish Church,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. 3. and the continuance vnder the Law, to the cleere mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation of Christ vnder the Gospell. And as the High Priest typified Christ himselfe, so the other, the Pastors of the Christian Church, and Christians.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:178475:35"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The manner of sacrificing followeth, either in spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall relation to the Priests alone, or in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon obseruation of some things belonging both to the Priests and people together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 The duties belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Priest, are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly expressed, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 8. 9. and the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation of Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, &amp; approuall of that which was done by thē, according to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, Chap. 9. vers. 23, 24. and Chap. 26. Secondly, his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments executed vpon the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:178475:35"/> transgressors, <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> Chap. 10. and Chap. 26.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the Priest &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, were sanctification, and this either Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall or morall.</p>
                  <p>Ceremoniall, of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, in the vse of some meats, &amp; abstinence frō other, and likewise from some persons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Of meats, Chap. 11. All were accounted cleane, from the fall to <hi>Moses</hi> time, but then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of them were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced vncleane: not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:178475:36"/> that these things were faulty in themselues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that estate wherin God created them, who made thē all very good; but were appointed by <hi>Moses</hi> Law to distinguish the <hi>Iew</hi> and the <hi>Gentile,</hi> and forbiddeth grosse behauiours in men that oftentimes become sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall like beasts.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Personall pollution, in regard whereof Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall sanctification was necessary. 1. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching women in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, Chap. 12. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Leprous persons or houses, Chapters 13,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:178475:36"/> 14. Thirdly, or by flux, Chap. 15.</p>
                  <p>Common sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on followeth, which was both in respect of the Priest and people, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 16, 17. where, of annuall rites concerning <hi>Aarons</hi> comming into the Sanctuary, his obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ornament, and time of purification for sinne.</p>
                  <p>Morall Sanctification followeth, and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther personall or reall.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Concerning our selues, Chap. 18. for marriage, which ought not to be in persons neer vnto vs in blood; nor
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:178475:37"/> with women in their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Respecting God &amp; our neighbours in nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue precepts, Chapters 19, 20.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Speciall institution concerning the Priests, Chap. 21.</p>
                  <p>Reall;</p>
                  <p>Of abuse in eating and offering.</p>
                  <p>And concerning times of certaine festiuities e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery yeer, &amp; these either partly in their vnsettled estate in the wildernesse, Chap. 23. or after that they were stated in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> euery seuenth yeer,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:178475:37"/> and euery fiftieth yeere, Chap. 25.</p>
                  <p>Voluntary, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vowes, Chap. 27. and <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. but with this difference, that in this booke they are set downe, onely as they were to bee performed: but in <hi>Numbers,</hi> as they were to bee performed or redeemed.</p>
                  <p>The obsignation of all, by a diuers effect. 1. of blessednesse in a right performāce of the things commanded; or 2. of cursing, in the contrary, Chap. 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Numbers" type="book">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:178475:38"/>
                  <head>NVMBERS</head>
                  <p>THE Booke of <hi>Numbers</hi> hath it name of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, and either of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons or places that were numbred, by <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the Princes of the Tribes. The Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story contayneth Acts done, and Lawes made from the beginning of the second moneth after their going forth of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> to the beginning of the 11. moneth of the fortieth yeere.</p>
                  <p>Concerning persons
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:178475:38"/> that were numbred, they are considered generally or specially.</p>
                  <p>The totall of all the people that came into <hi>Canaan,</hi> were six hundred and three thousand fiue hundred &amp; fiftie, Chap. 1. 46. <hi>Leui</hi> exempted, vers. 47.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Persons in speciall are diuersly ranked and disposed.</p>
                  <p>Ciuill, as the chiefe of the seuerall Tribes, Cha. 2. and 7. and the Priests and Leuites who were numbred onely once, Chap. 3.</p>
                  <p>The disposing of these
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:178475:39"/> and the rest was by order Ciuill, sutable to warre, or sacred.</p>
                  <p>According to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the people marched according to their Tribes euery one vnder their chiefe Captaine, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, 2. 10. The Priests office was to beare the Arke, when it remoued, on their shoulders, and to blowe the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, Chap. 10. The Leuites were to serue the Priests in the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, but not to come neere the Sanctuary. 2. to helpe to carry the Tabernacle, when it was
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:178475:39"/> to be borne.</p>
                  <p>In their march, note the places from whence they went, the places whither, the manner how, and the effects.</p>
                  <p>The place where they were first numbred was at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> in the wildernesse, Chap. 1. The second time at the time at the plaine of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab,</hi> Chap. 26.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The number of their iourneyes or places of their remooue were 42. particularly layd downe, Chap 33.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The manner, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection was by a cloud,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:178475:40"/> Chap. 10. 34. and a set forme of prayer vsed by <hi>Moses,</hi> as they went or rested, vers. 35, 36.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The successe (as of all warre) was diuers, good or euill, so that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they might haue come into <hi>Canaan</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few dayes, in regard of distance of places, yet were they many yeeres in performing it, &amp; that</p>
                  <p n="1">1 In respect of Gods prouidence, that would thereby exercise and try them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 In regard of opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made against them;</p>
                  <p n="1">1 By others.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:178475:40"/>
                  <p n="1"> 1 As <hi>Edom,</hi> Chap. 20. 14. and <hi>Sehon</hi> King of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Israel</hi> passage. And by <hi>Arad</hi> King of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and <hi>Og</hi> King of <hi>Bashan,</hi> Chap. 21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 By Magicke Art, and subornation of <hi>Balack</hi> to haue <hi>Balaam</hi> curse <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> Chapters 22, 23, 24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 By their owne sins, as of <hi>Murmuring.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 For the tediousnesse of the way in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of <hi>Paran,</hi> hauing trauelled 3. dayes, for which fire came out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, Chap. 11. 1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 For want of flesh at
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:178475:41"/>
                     <hi>Kibroth-Hattauah;</hi> for which the plague came among them, Chap. 11. vers. 33.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 At <hi>Hazaroth, Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> murmur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Moses,</hi> for which she became Leprous, ch. 12. 10.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 At <hi>Rithma</hi> in <hi>Paran</hi> the spies were sent forth, Chap. 13. and their des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, murmuring &amp; impatience is punished, in that the Elders dyed in the wildernesse, their posterity wandered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long time therein; and the spies were sodainely consumed, Chap. 14.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:178475:41"/>
                  <p n="5"> 5 The earth opened and swallowed vp <hi>Corah</hi> and his Complices that rebelled against <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and all their goods, Chap. 16. 31, 32.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 And the people that would not acknowledge <hi>Moses</hi> the Lords Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, and <hi>Aaron</hi> his Priest, were punished with death, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of foureteene thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand and seuen hundred, vers. 49.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 At <hi>Kadesh, Moses, Aaron</hi> and the people murmur for want of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for which they are denyed entrance into the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:178475:42"/> land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Ch. 20.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 For murmuring through tediousnesse of the way from mount <hi>Hor</hi> to <hi>Punon</hi> in <hi>Zalmona,</hi> they were stung with fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery Serpents, Chap. 21.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hitherto of their Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, and the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof. 2. Of their Idolatry and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication at the plaine of <hi>Moab;</hi> where, of the manner &amp; punishment, accordingly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>First, the manner by the wicked Counsell of <hi>Balaam,</hi> giuen, Chap. 24. 14. and embraced, Cha. 25.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:178475:42"/>
                  <p n="2"> 2 The punishment fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thereupon, was executed vpō the actors and authors, both of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> and their enemies.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Of <hi>Israel</hi> for this sin, there dyed of the plague 2400. and all the heads of the people hanged vp, and <hi>Zimri</hi> thrust tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, Chap. 25.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of <hi>Midian</hi> was slaine <hi>Cozbi,</hi> Chap. 25. and <hi>Balak,</hi> and the fiue Kings of <hi>Midian. Balaam</hi> was controlled by his Asse, and afterwards slaine; and so likewise were al the males of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> and the women
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:178475:43"/> who had lyen by man, Chap. 31. Insomuch that of all them who were numbred at Mount <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai,</hi> not any came into <hi>Canaan,</hi> but <hi>Caleb</hi> &amp; <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shua,</hi> Chap. 26. 64.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hitherto of the ill suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse that</hi> Israel <hi>had; that which fell out more prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously after that God was appeased by the zeale of</hi> Phineas, <hi>followeth; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we haue to note, touching persons and possessions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 Persons were either such as deuided <hi>Canaan;</hi> or those to whom the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision was made.</p>
                  <p>The deuiders were <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leazur,</hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:178475:43"/>
                     <hi>Ioshua,</hi> and one select person out of the seuerall Tribes, Chap. 34. whose charge it was to see, that no more were deuided then was right, nor any left out which appertained to them.</p>
                  <p>They whom this diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion concerned.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 None but such as could deriue their discēt from <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 Of Ciuill persons, the inheritance was to passe to the males, but in case of defect thereof, the daughters were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, as in the example of <hi>Zelophehads</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:178475:44"/> of the Tribe of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasseh,</hi> Chap. 27. who were to match within the familie of the Tribe of their Fathers, Cha. 36.</p>
                  <p>Of sacred persons were the Leuites, who had for themselues 48. Cities &amp; their suburbes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Possession, was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on this side <hi>Iordan,</hi> as of the Tribe of <hi>Ruben, Gad,</hi> and halfe Tribe of <hi>Manasseh,</hi> Chap. 32. or beyond <hi>Iordan,</hi> as of the other nine Tribes &amp; half Tribe of <hi>Manasseh,</hi> all which were deuided by <hi>Lot.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Deuteronomy" type="book">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:178475:44"/>
                  <head>Deuteronomie.</head>
                  <p>THIS Booke of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth a repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of some things, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of other.</p>
                  <p>It was necessary that some things should bee explained, because they were obscure, and not obserued of the people, as of iourneying from Mount <hi>Horeb</hi> at GODS Comandement, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the mountain of the <hi>Amorites.</hi> 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the institution of Magistrates, and narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:178475:45"/> of things done at se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall times, Chap. 1. Of warre and peace, &amp; with whom, Chap. 2. and 3. This History then is of those things which were done from their being at Mount <hi>Horeb,</hi> and in the plaine of <hi>Moab,</hi> where (as is thought) this book was written by <hi>Moses.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The repetition is of the Law of God, Moral, Ceremoniall, and Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall.</p>
                  <p>The Morall, enioyning constāt obedience to the Law of God, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or detraction; by many arguments, Ch. 4.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:178475:45"/> Of blessing and cursing, Ch. 5. From their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to obey it, Chap. 6. Continuall practice that should bee of the Law, Chap. 7. Of resolution, not to partake with Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, Chap. 8. From Gods trayning them so long in the wildernes to fit them for <hi>Canaan,</hi> Ch. 9. Of Gods meere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to estate them there, Chap. 11. As of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and of the stablenes of Gods goodnesse to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, Chap. 12. For caution, by reason of Idolaters among them, Chap. 13. From the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:178475:46"/> to be vsed against seducers.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Ceremoniall Law followeth:</head>
                     <p>Chap. 14. Against Heathenish customes, &amp; legall pollution by eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                     <p>Chap. 15. Of set times reserued for the benefit of the poore seruants and others.</p>
                     <p>Chap. 16. Of festiual times such as were,</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Of Easter, in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their deliuery out of <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 12. held in the first moneth, the foureteenth day of the moneth.</p>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:178475:46"/>
                     <p n="2"> 2 Of Pentecost, <hi>Exo.</hi> 19. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23. &amp; <hi>Numb.</hi> 28. In remembrance of the Law of God giuen on the fiftieth day after their comming forth of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 Of Tabernacles, to put them in minde how their Fathers dwelled in Boothes in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the space of 40. yeeres. This Feast was kept on the 15. day of the seuenth moneth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Iudiciall Lawes follow:</head>
                     <p n="1">1 Generall, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all.</p>
                     <p>Chap. 17. Of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:178475:47"/> of offences by legall course.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Singuler,</p>
                     <p>Chap. 18. Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the Leuites maintenance, and against false Prophets. Chap. 19. The people are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in Law cases, by due proceeding. Chap. 20. Rules for warre ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within the Land of Promise, or out of it. Cha. 21. By other mens suffering for euill, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of doing euill.</p>
                     <p>Chap. 22. to 26. Of charity, which ought to be shewed in all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Chap. 24. and 25.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:178475:47"/> Of Matrimony. Chap. 26. Of iustice in the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of first fruits and Tythes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Confirmation of all these Lawes.</head>
                     <p>Chap. 27. By Signes and threatnings. Chap. 28. By blessings and imprecations; the like whereunto <hi>Leuit,</hi> 26. but here with inlargement. Chap. 29. A renewing of the Couenant with <hi>Israel,</hi> which had beene made with thē at Mount <hi>Horeb,</hi> where the Law was giuen, shewing what they should expect vpon breach of the couenant.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:178475:48"/> Chap. 30. That their sins were pardonable on condition of repentāce, and not otherwise. Ch. 31. Teaching publike persons to leaue things well settled after their death, Chap. 32. In ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as the former, with a Prophecy of the Iewish people, and of their fall, punishment &amp; restitutiō. Chap. 33. <hi>Moses</hi> fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, and blessing by name of all the Tribes, <hi>Leui</hi> especially, <hi>Simeon</hi> onely excepted, whether for his sinne in selling <hi>Ioseph;</hi> or for cruelty, to the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> or being
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:178475:48"/> cause of Irreligion, &amp;c. Chap. 34. Of <hi>Moses</hi> death and commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Which part (as some thinke) was set downe by <hi>Ioshua</hi> his successor.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Joshua" type="book">
                  <head>IOSHVA.</head>
                  <p>HItherto of the Law, the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Prophets, now come in, so called because they wrote Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories, such as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Bookes of <hi>Ioshua, Iudges, Samuel,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Kings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:178475:49"/>
                  <p>The memorable acts done by <hi>Ioshua,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in this booke, are of yeeres 18. or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, wherein is shewed the estate of the Childrē of <hi>Israel</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods promise with <hi>Ioshua</hi> their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; where, of the Countrey of <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; then of their settling therein.</p>
                  <p>The Countrey which Gods people inhabited, was diuersly styled in many respects.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Of the <hi>Gentiles, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> the Son of <hi>Cham,</hi> the Northerly part, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestina,</hi>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:178475:49"/> being deuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three parts, <hi>Galile, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, Iudea; Galile</hi> most northerly, <hi>Phaenicia</hi> We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterly, <hi>Caelosyria</hi> on the East, and <hi>Samaria</hi> with <hi>Arabia</hi> inclosing it Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly; <hi>Iordan</hi> parteth it in the middest. <hi>Galile</hi> is called, of the <hi>Gentiles, Mat.</hi> 4. 15. because it was neere to <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sydon. Samaria</hi> is seated betweene <hi>Galile</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudea,</hi> and much lesse then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 After <hi>Ioshuas</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering of this Coūtry, it was called the land of <hi>Israel.</hi> After the renting
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:178475:50"/> of it in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> time, one part was called <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> and the other, <hi>Iudah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 After the Captiuity, it was properly called <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daea,</hi> &amp; the people <hi>Iewes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 Of Christians, it was called the holy land, and for the ancient fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse thereof, sayd to flow with milk &amp; hony.</p>
                  <p>In the establishing of this Countrey, obserue, the planter, and manner of the plantation.</p>
                  <p>The planter was <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shua,</hi> of <hi>Iosephs</hi> house, who giueth the pleasant soyle to <hi>Iudah,</hi> which <hi>Moses</hi> had so bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:178475:50"/> by Prophecie, and <hi>Samuel</hi> by anoynting <hi>Dauid</hi> of that Tribe King. If <hi>Iudah</hi> had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided it, the Heathen would haue thought it great partiality, but Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph doth it, planting <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> in the best soyle.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Their plantation first by the remouing of their enemies, and settling in their places afterwards.</p>
                  <p>The places and Kings that were subdued, are noted, Chap. 12. the manner of their supplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, either by weake meanes, as of <hi>Iericho,</hi> Chap. 1. without means,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:178475:51"/> by astonishment, Cha. 2. 11. by miraculous means as staying the course of the waters, Chapt. 3. 16. and standing of the sunne &amp; moone, Ch. 10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Of the plantation in <hi>Canaan</hi> of all the Tribes, saue of <hi>Ruben, Gad,</hi> and halfe Tribe of <hi>Manasseh</hi> that were plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beyond <hi>Iordan,</hi> Cha. 13. and 14, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Judges" type="book">
                  <head>IVDGES.</head>
                  <p>HItherto of the <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelits</hi> in vnsettled estate, and in war;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:178475:51"/> now of them in peace, <hi>Ioshua</hi> their Captaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, and they vnder the gouernment of <hi>Iudges</hi> (wherof this Booke hath it name penned by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel;)</hi> where, of their vocation and office.</p>
                  <p>The Iudges were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons extraordinarily stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp by God, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as warriours for that time; not made by electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the first Kings, nor by succession, as the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but by Gods imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate raising of them vp. Their office is implyed in their names, Iudges of iudging, and of persons iudged.</p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:178475:52"/>
                  <p>The names and time of gouernement of most of these Iudges were,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Othniel</hi> of <hi>Iudah,</hi> Chap. 3. vers. 9, 10, 11. that gouerned 40. y. and deliuered thē out of the hands of the <hi>Aramites.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Ehud</hi> of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> vers. 15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Shamgar,</hi> who ruled 80. yeeres, vers. 30. &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered them from the <hi>Moabites,</hi> and also from the <hi>Philistims,</hi> v. 31</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Debora</hi> of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> deliuered them from the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> Chapter 5. with <hi>Barak</hi> of <hi>Nepthali,</hi> vers. 10.</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:178475:52"/>
                  <p n="5"> 5 <hi>Gideon,</hi> 40. yeeres, &amp; deliuered them from the <hi>Midianites,</hi> Chapters 6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abimelech</hi> of <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im,</hi> 3. yeeres, Chap. 9. <hi>Thola</hi> 23. yeeres of <hi>Issa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. Iair,</hi> of <hi>Manasses,</hi> yeeres 22. Chapter 10. <hi>Iepthe</hi> of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> yeeres 6. <hi>Ihsan</hi> of <hi>Bethlem</hi> in the Tribe of <hi>Iudah. Elon</hi> of <hi>Zabulon,</hi> yeeres 10. Cha. 10. <hi>Abdon</hi> of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> 8. yeeres, Chapter 12. <hi>Samson</hi> of <hi>Dan,</hi> yeeres 20. &amp; deliuerd them from the <hi>Philistims,</hi> Chap. 16. <hi>Eli,</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> who was of <hi>Leui,</hi> recouereth the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:178475:53"/> Ark to <hi>Iuda,</hi> both which are recorded in the 1. of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and iudged <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> 20. yeeres.</p>
                  <p>Concerning these, some had the preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence for multitude, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for dignity.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Was <hi>Iosephs</hi> house, for which they despised <hi>Iudah,</hi> 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 16. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 1. which was the cause of his ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 For dignity, and so was <hi>Iuda,</hi> because Christ came of that Tribe.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto of the <hi>Iudges;</hi> the persons iudged were their enemies; and they
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:178475:53"/> occasioned by their sins. Their fals were many, first, before their possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Secondly, and so after their refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and hauing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sinnes, had necessarily many enemies accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; who their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were, may appeare in the reading of this Booke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Ruth" type="book">
                  <head>RVTH.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Gentiles</hi> crums let fall from the Iewes Table, as
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:178475:54"/> appeareth in this Booke (made in the dayes of the Iudges) in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Ruth,</hi> of whom obserue what she was by birth, and new birth.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 By the first, she was a Gentile of <hi>Moab.</hi> 2. By the second, she is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the old and new Testament, ingrafted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy pedegree in the Tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Booz,</hi> of whom Christ came, <hi>Math.</hi> 1. So that Christ came a light to the Gentiles, wherof <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> womb was a token, out of which came two Nations.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:178475:54"/>
                  <p>The Gentiles of hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable note in Scripture, are, as <hi>Ruth</hi> here, so <hi>Iob</hi> in the land of <hi>Hus, Naaman</hi> in <hi>Syria, Rahab</hi> in <hi>Iericho</hi> of <hi>Chams house,</hi> the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Canaan. Naamah</hi> descended of <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> the incestuous sons of <hi>Lot,</hi> and great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the Church, and yet from her came the Royall blood of the Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 13. and Christ came of <hi>Thamar, Gen.</hi> 38. 14. neither were some others excluded that came of <hi>Ismael, Esay</hi> 66.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:178475:55"/>
                  <head>An Introduction followeth to the Bookes <hi>of the KINGS.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>Hitherto of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the preseruation of his people by Patriarkes, Captaines, &amp; Iudges: Now of Kings, which are (or should be) nursing Fathers of the Church; where first, what they were, &amp; of their Ordination.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>KIngs are the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, set ouer people and Kingdomes for the gouernment thereof in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:178475:55"/> wealth, peace and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, by good lawes fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med according to the Lawes of God.</p>
                  <p>Of Kings, some were very ancient among the Heathen, <hi>Gen.</hi> 36. 31. and others more lately.</p>
                  <p>The Kings of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions had Crownes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them by the people; God putting it into their heads, to acknowledge them for their King.</p>
                  <p>Kings among Gods people, were immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chosen by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, &amp; the people only gaue obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:178475:56"/>
                  <p>People therefore beeing precipitate in their courses, vnlesse that Lawes (the rule of good life, and restraint of euill) bee held in the hands of the supreame Magistrate (who is the keeper of both tables) sheweth the calling of Kings very expedient.</p>
                  <p>It was necessary that the estate of KINGS shold now come in, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinds of gouernmēt cease, to fulfill the Word and the worke of God.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 His Word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that Kings should come of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:178475:56"/> him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 6. the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile thereof vpon <hi>Isaaks</hi> posterity, and <hi>Iacobs</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 10.</p>
                  <p>That the Scepter should not depart from <hi>Iudah.</hi> And therefore though <hi>Saul</hi> were King, yet because he was not of <hi>Iudah,</hi> but of <hi>Beniamin</hi> the Lord crossed him, &amp; the Machabees of <hi>Leui</hi> vsurping the Kingdome, were punished of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The worke of God, for building the glorious Temple of SALOMON; where commeth in the Fift Age containing 419 <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The</hi> 5. <hi>Age.</hi>
                     </note> yeeres, continuing vnto
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:178475:57"/> the Captiuity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> expressed in the second of Kings, Chap. 24. 25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple could not conueniently bee builded by the <hi>Iudges,</hi> nor by <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Dauid:</hi> not by the <hi>Iudges,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of their weaknesse and pouerty, and their change of gouernment; nor by <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Dauid,</hi> because they had many troubles: therefore the worke was accomplished in the daies of <hi>Salomon,</hi> that were full of peace and plenty.</p>
                  <p>In the treaty of Kings, the bookes are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:178475:57"/> where they are recorded, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent manner of setting downe the history of them.</p>
                  <p>The bookes intreating of Kings, are considered according to their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and appellation.</p>
                  <p>In most Bibles there are sixe distinct bookes, that do principally make mention of KINGS: Whereof two are enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled of <hi>Samuel,</hi> two of the <hi>Kings,</hi> and likewise two of <hi>Chronicles;</hi> but the Hebrewes doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies style the foure for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer bookes onely, by
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:178475:58"/> the name of Kings, and doe make the two Books of <hi>Chronicles</hi> but one, which the Grecians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the length, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide into two.</p>
                  <p>The two former haue the name of <hi>Samuel,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they doe intreate of him and the 2. Kings that he anoynted, <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="1 Samuel" type="book">
                  <head>1. SAMVEL.</head>
                  <p>COncerning <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> his birth &amp; acts are considerable.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:178475:58"/>
                  <p n="1"> 1 Was borne in <hi>Rama,</hi> where also he was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Chap. 25. 1. and 28. 3. the sonne of godly Parents, <hi>Elkanah,</hi> and <hi>Hanna,</hi> Chap. 1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 His acts, as they stand in relation to God, <hi>Eli, Saul, Dauid,</hi> and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Israel</hi> in generall.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Towards God, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing attentiue to his call, Chap. 3. and obedient thereunto in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his place.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Declareth to <hi>Eli</hi> Gods decree concerning his house, and <hi>Israel,</hi> Ch. 3. The effects whereof doe follow, Chapters 4,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:178475:59"/> 5, 6, 7, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The calling of <hi>Saul</hi> is foretold by <hi>Samuel,</hi> and confirmations of it, Chapters 9, 10, 11. after that, hee was desired of the people for their King, to their ruine, Chap. 8. The sinnes of <hi>Saul</hi> were many. He v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surped the Priests office, Chap. 13. spared <hi>Agag,</hi> Chap. 15. Iustified his sin, <hi>ibid.</hi> Slew the Lords Priests, Chap. 22. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted with witches. Ch. 28. And touching <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> hee enuied his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and good successe; would haue murthered
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:178475:59"/> and betrayed him, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 18, 19. And would haue slaine his owne son for louing him, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 20.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 To <hi>Dauid,</hi> who was thrice anoynted King, first, by <hi>Samuel</hi> in <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> 1. <hi>Samuel</hi> 16. 4, 13. afterwards by the Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> in <hi>Hebron,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 4. by all the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Israel</hi> in <hi>Hebron,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. 3. of whose persecution, and death of his persecutor to the end of this Booke.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 To the people of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> for which he praied, and aduised, Ch. 12, 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2 Samuel" type="book">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:178475:60"/>
                  <head>2. SAMVEL.</head>
                  <p>HItherto of <hi>Dauids</hi> troubles in the daies of <hi>Saul,</hi> now of them afterwards, and they outward or inward; partly in the posterity of <hi>Saul,</hi> and afterwards in his owne Children, and others, &amp; of Gods iustice and mercy to <hi>Dauid</hi> in them all, set forth by the metaphor of Gods rod and staffe, <hi>Psal.</hi> 23. 4.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The enemie of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> of the race of <hi>Saul,</hi> was <hi>Ishbosheth</hi> his Sonne, competitor for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:178475:60"/> Chapters 1, 2. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Gods staffe by the death of <hi>Ishbosheth,</hi> Chap. 4. the loue of his chiefe subiects, that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oynted him their King. His Marriages and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of his enemies, as of the <hi>Philistims</hi> twice, Chap. 5. and of them, &amp; other enemies, Chap. 8. and of the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> and <hi>Aramites</hi> in the case of <hi>Hanun,</hi> Chap. 10. and by bringing backe the Arke, Chap. 6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The more inward troubles of <hi>Dauid</hi> were occasioned by his owne sinnes.</p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:178475:61"/>
                  <p n="1"> 1 Of Adultery and murther, Chap. 11.</p>
                  <p>Gods rod; the death of his childe, Chap. 12. The Conspiracy of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salom,</hi> Chap. 15. the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest of <hi>Amnon,</hi> Cha. 13. The rayling &amp; reuiling of <hi>Shemei,</hi> Chap. 16. the rebellion of <hi>Sheba,</hi> Cha. 20. Gods staffe; his childe was receiued to mercy, Chap. 12. <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salom</hi> is ouerthrowne, Chap. 18. <hi>Dauid</hi> is roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally attended to <hi>Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> Cha. 19. The head of <hi>Sheba</hi> is cut off, Chap. 20. and afterwards the <hi>Philistims,</hi> that waged
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:178475:61"/> warre so often against him, are conquered, Ch. 21.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The same more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate before <hi>Dauids</hi> death, was his pride to number the people, Ch. 24.</p>
                  <p>Gods rod, in the death of 70. thousand. His staffe; the plague ceased: and afterward, <hi>Dauid</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in peace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1 Kings" type="book">
                  <head>1. KINGS.</head>
                  <p>OF Kings by ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> or by succession,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:178475:62"/> as 2. <hi>Samuel,</hi> hath beene already spoken. Now of the estate of Monarchie set foorth in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Israel,</hi> and that either in the increase, or decrease thereof.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 In the dayes of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> before it was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, (as afterwards it was.) 2. In the decrease thereof either in <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> time, or in those Kings that came after him.</p>
                  <p>In the increase, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of <hi>Salomon</hi> is to bee considered as touching his Coronation &amp; acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as they were perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:178475:62"/> to Chapter 11.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 His Coronation is set forth by the oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Adoniah</hi> his elder brother, the son of <hi>Dauid</hi> by <hi>Haggith,</hi> and frustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, in that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> is made King, c. 1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Salomons</hi> actions do follow in relation to God or man.</p>
                  <p>To God, whom hee petitioneth, first, for wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to gouerne Gods people, Chap. 3. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for a blessing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods house, Chap. 8. which he had builded in most sumptuous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Chapters 5, 6, 7. &amp;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:178475:63"/> the gracious answer that hee had from GOD in both, and aboue that hee desired.</p>
                  <p>To man, the improue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his wisedome, in the execution of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, according to Gods Law, and his Fathers Testament, on malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Chap. 2. and by decision of matters in controuersie, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause of the people therein, Chap. 3.</p>
                  <p>The decrease of the Kingdome either in the dayes of <hi>Salomon,</hi> or in those Kings that succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him of <hi>Iudah</hi> or <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:178475:63"/>
                  <p>The Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> and of <hi>Israel,</hi> are first na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and then sorted, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they were condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, or as they and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heathen Kings were in time together.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> were</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Salomon, Rehoboam, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biam, Asa, Iehosaphat, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horam, Ahaziah, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah, Ioash, Amasiah, Aza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah, Iotham, Ahaz, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah, Manasses, Amon, Iosiah, Iehoahaz, Iehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim, Iehoiachin, Zedekiah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> were</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ieroboam, Nadab, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asha,</hi>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:178475:64"/>
                     <hi>Elah, Zimri, Tibni, Omri, Ahab, Ahaziah, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horam, Iehu, Iehoahaz, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ash, Ieroboam, Zacharia, Shallum, Menahem, Peka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiah, Pekah, Hoshea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 The Kings of <hi>Iudah, Israel,</hi> and other that then liued in time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rehoboam</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam</hi> King of <hi>Israel,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 12. 20. and <hi>Shishak</hi> King of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> Chap. 14. 25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abiam</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 15. 1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Asa</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> vers. 9. <hi>Nadab</hi> vers. 25. <hi>Baasha,</hi> 28. <hi>Elah,</hi> Chap. 16. vers.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:178475:64"/> 8. <hi>Zimri,</hi> 10. <hi>Omri</hi> 16. and <hi>Ahab</hi> 28. all Kings of <hi>Israel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iehosaphat</hi> &amp; <hi>Ahab</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 22. 4. 41. and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haziah,</hi> 49. <hi>Iehoram</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 3. 1. and <hi>Benha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad</hi> King of <hi>Aram,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 20. 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iehoram</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Iehoram</hi> King of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sha</hi> King of <hi>Moab,</hi> Chap. 3. vers. 4. and King of <hi>Edom</hi> 9. and <hi>Benhadad,</hi> Chap. 6. 24.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ahaziah</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 8. 24. <hi>Ioram</hi> son of <hi>Ahab</hi> 28. &amp; <hi>Iehu</hi> that conspired against <hi>Ioram</hi> Ch. 9.</p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:178475:65"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Athaliah</hi> and <hi>Iehu</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioash</hi> King of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Athaliah,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11. <hi>Iehu,</hi> Chap. 12. 1. <hi>Iehoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haz</hi> his son, Chap. 13. 1, 10. and <hi>Hazael</hi> King of <hi>Aram,</hi> Chap. 12. 18. who now vexed <hi>Israel,</hi> Chap. 13. 22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amaziah</hi> &amp; <hi>Iehoash</hi> king of <hi>Israel,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 14. 1. &amp; <hi>Ieroboam</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Azariah</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 15. 1. <hi>Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> his son, 8. <hi>Shallum,</hi> 10. <hi>Menachem,</hi> 14, 17. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kahiah,</hi> 23. <hi>Pekah,</hi> 27. <hi>Pul</hi> King of <hi>Ashur,</hi> 19. <hi>Tig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lath Pileser</hi> likewise king
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:178475:65"/> of <hi>Ashur,</hi> 29.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iotham</hi> and <hi>Pekah,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 32. and <hi>Rezin</hi> the King of <hi>Aram,</hi> 37. <hi>Ahaz</hi> and <hi>Pekah</hi> and <hi>Rezin,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 16. and <hi>Hoshea,</hi> Ch. 17. 1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Hoshea,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 18. 1. <hi>Salmane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser</hi> King of <hi>Ashur,</hi> 11. <hi>Sennacherib.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Manasses,</hi> carried away Captiue by the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the host of the King of <hi>Ashur,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ammon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iosiah</hi> &amp; <hi>Pharaoh Neco</hi> king of <hi>Egypt,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 23. 29.</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:178475:66"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iehoiakim,</hi> and <hi>Pharoah Necho,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 23, 34. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> Chap. 24. 2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iehoiachim,</hi> and <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 24. 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 24. 25</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Of the forenamed, some are set downe in the first, and others in the second bookes of the <hi>Kings.</hi> In the former, is the story of fiue Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> from <hi>Salomon</hi> to <hi>Iehosaphat,</hi> with the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of <hi>Iehoram,</hi> his sonne, Chap. 22. 50. and of eight Kings of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, from <hi>Ieroboam</hi> to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:178475:66"/>
                     <hi>Achab;</hi> and namely, of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> his son, that succeeded him in his Kingdome, <hi>verse</hi> 40.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Salomon,</hi> (peaceable) called also <hi>Iedidiah,</hi> of the loue of God to him. Of whose posteritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; now, of the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning estate of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in his time, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the cause and effect. The cause, his Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry by strange wiues. The effects are, the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Gods Iustice thereupon, either more immediately during his life, by enemies that came vp against him; as
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:178475:67"/>
                     <hi>Adad</hi> the <hi>Edomite, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon</hi> King of <hi>Damascus,</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam</hi> his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, after his death, in his posterity from <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam</hi> his sonne, to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coniah,</hi> in whom the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall line of <hi>Salomon</hi> endeth.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> (large a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people) 1. in possessions in the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his father <hi>Salomon:</hi> but the contrary fell out; by the iustice of God, punishing the sinne of <hi>Salomon</hi> for his owne sinnes: and likewise hee being an Idolater, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:178475:67"/> improuident, by negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the aduice of his sage Counsellours, and listening to young men: the effects wherof were,</p>
                  <p>The losse of tenne Tribes, and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from God not to fight to bring them back againe, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 11. 4. his enemies spoile his treasures, the Citie, and the Temple, Chap. 12. he raigned 18. yeeres.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Abiah,</hi> his sonne, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. <hi>(My Father is Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah)</hi> or <hi>Abiam, (my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the Sea)</hi> proud tytles, and the latter (as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:178475:68"/> is most probable) as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed after his great vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie obtained against <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 14. 17. but yet did neuer, neither could vnite the Kingdomes vnder one gouernment.</p>
                  <p>He was religious in shew, but without soūd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 13. hee raigned 3. yeeres.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Asa,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Abiam,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 15. 8. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. <hi>(Destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)</hi> whether of Idolatry, or outward enemies of his peace, or of both; which he did in part: for 1. he expelled the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites.</hi>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:178475:68"/> 2. deposed his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous mother. 3. &amp; purged his Countrey of Idolatry. 4. fortifies his Territories.</p>
                  <p>But vnanswerable to his name afterwards.</p>
                  <p>1 Was strangely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by <hi>Baasha</hi> King of Israel, that warred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him. 2. Couenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with <hi>Benhadad,</hi> who therevpon brake the League with <hi>Baasha.</hi> 3. Being reprooued for the same from the Lord; persecuteth the Prophet, and oppresseth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. and 4. in his disease, preferres a Phisician be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:178475:69"/>
                  <p>He raigned 41. yeeres.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Iehosaphat,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> Chap. 19, 20. <hi>(The Lord iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth)</hi> to assure him of Gods protection &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, relying vpon him: which he had experiēce of,</p>
                  <p>Abolishing Idolatry, building Cities, conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring enemies: But shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his infirmities, by his affinitie with <hi>Ahab,</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with him, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with <hi>Ahaziah</hi> the sonne of <hi>Ahab,</hi> to the losse of his name, 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> Chap. 22. hee raigned 25. yeeres.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:178475:69"/>
                     <head>Hitherto of the Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> in this Booke: the Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> doe followe.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>IEroboam,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> Chapters 11, 12, 13, 14. the sonne of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat,</hi> a branch come out of Aegypt, of the house of <hi>Ioseph,</hi> by his marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with an Aegyptian woman; a scourge to the people of God, and the wracke of Religion many hundred yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The vtter enemy of <hi>Iudah,</hi> by raising vp <hi>Shyshak</hi> against it. 2. by erecting two golden
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:178475:70"/> Calues for worship, and so prouoking GOD Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them. He raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 22. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Nadab.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 15. an Idolater, slaine by <hi>Baasha.</hi> Raigned 2. yeers</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Baasha,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Ahijah</hi> of the house of <hi>Issachar,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 15. 27. an Idolater. Raigned 24. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>Elah,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Baasha,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 16. 6. a prophane person, drū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and murthered in his drunkennes by <hi>Zim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rj</hi> his seruant; He raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned yeeres 2.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 <hi>Zimri</hi> succeedeth in
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:178475:70"/> the place of <hi>Elah,</hi> his Master, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 16. slay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the house of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asha,</hi> a murtherer of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, by fyring his owne Palace: hee raigned se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen dayes.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 <hi>Tibni,</hi> Chap. 16. slaine in opposition with <hi>Omri.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7 <hi>Omri,</hi> Chap. 16. 25. the worst of all before him, he raigned 12. yeres</p>
                     <p n="8">8 <hi>Ahab,</hi> Chap. 16. vers. 30. 33. The worst of all before him, which appeareth in many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars; first, in that hee was a notable Idolater himselfe. 2. In his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:178475:71"/> with <hi>Iesabel,</hi> the patronesse of Idolaters, and they both cruell per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors and oppressors.</p>
                     <p>The persons persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them, of speciall note, were <hi>Eliah,</hi> of whō from Chap. 17. to 21. &amp; <hi>Michaiah,</hi> Chap 22. 27. the party oppressed was <hi>Naboth</hi> for his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, Chap. 21.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eliah</hi> is set forth to be a Prophet of God, by that which God did for him, and against his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors; the former is manifest,</p>
                     <p>First, by miraculous preseruation of his life in
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:178475:71"/> the time of drought and famine, by the meanes of Rauens, Chap. 17. &amp; by Angels, Cha. 19. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, is secured against <hi>Ahab</hi> when he met him, Chap. 18. and obtaineth raine, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 By that which at <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> appointment was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted vpō <hi>Baals</hi> Priests, Chap. 18. or that which by his prediction God would doe vpon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of Idolatry &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Chap. 21. vers. 21. &amp;c. and the execution thereof vpon <hi>Ahab,</hi> Ch. 22. 38. and on <hi>Iezabel,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> Chap. 9. and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:178475:72"/> the euill that came vpon good <hi>Iehoshaphat</hi> for ouermuch familiaritie with him, 1. <hi>King.</hi> c. 22. He raigned 22. yeeres.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2 Kings" type="book">
                  <head>2. KINGS.</head>
                  <p>WHEREIN is intreated of the decrease of both the said King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and the degrees thereof in the raigne of seuerall Kings, vntill the vtter desolation of <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Iudah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this booke obserue,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:178475:72"/> concerning the remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able actions of some Prophets and Kings.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>The principall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets herein mentioned, are <hi>Eliah</hi> and <hi>Elisha,</hi> and of them ioyntly and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally.</p>
                     <p>First, of them together before <hi>Eliah</hi> was taken vp, &amp; therein of <hi>Elishaes</hi> loue vnto him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest made, and obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Chap. 2.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Seuered, in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation of <hi>Elisha</hi> to be a rare Prophet, Chap. 2. and by foretelling the successe of warre at <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaphats</hi> request against
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:178475:73"/> the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> Ch. 3. And by many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles wrought by him, Chapters 4, 5, 6 by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of wonderfull plenty in the time of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme famine, Chap. 7. and also of 7. yeeres fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in the time of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Chap. 8.</p>
                     <p>Of <hi>Benhadads</hi> death, and <hi>Hazaels</hi> raigne, and of the destruction of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, Chap. 9. vers. 7. or executed, first, in part vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Iehoram,</hi> vers. 24. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haziah,</hi> 27. <hi>Iezabel,</hi> 33. Second, totally, Chap. 10. vpon all the seede of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:178475:73"/>
                        <hi>Ahab</hi> his familiars, and Priests by the hand of <hi>Iehu;</hi> and the reason of all: To fulfill the Word of the Lord by <hi>Eliah,</hi> vers. 10. And lastly, by a dead man reuiuing, that was cast into the sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of <hi>Elisha,</hi> ch. 13. 21.</p>
                     <p>Hitherto of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the <hi>Kings</hi> doe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
                     <p>Where, of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and places where they are recorded.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 The totall of the Kings intreated of in this booke, are 28. of which 12. are of <hi>Israel,</hi> and of <hi>Iud,ah</hi> 16.</p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:178475:74"/>
                     <p n="2"> 2 The sorting of these, is either seuerally or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, as of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> Cha. 1. and of <hi>Iehoram</hi> the son of <hi>Ahab,</hi> Chap. 3. and of other Kings of <hi>Israel,</hi> to Chap. 14. from thence to the 18. of the misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble estate of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, with their mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all contentions, and the subuersion of <hi>Israel</hi> first, and of <hi>Iudah</hi> afterwards, by other Nations.</p>
                     <p>The Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Ahab,</hi> were,</p>
                     <p n="9">9. <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 22. 8. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 1. an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later, <hi>Moab</hi> rebelleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him: hee consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:178475:74"/> with an Idol for the cure of his malady: sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in fury for <hi>Elishah,</hi> that telleth his doome: but the messengers were consumed with fire from God. Hee raigned 2. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. <hi>Iehoram,</hi> brother to <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> and sonne of <hi>Ahab,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. 16. &amp;c. An Idolater, &amp; married <hi>Ahabs</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but was better than his father or mother, ch. 3. 2. was slaine by Iehu, Chapt. 9. 24. raigned 8. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. <hi>Iehu,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Nimshi.</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:178475:75"/> 9. 10. whereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the tract of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sha:</hi> but of his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on further; either euill, or good, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of God for that he did well.</p>
                     <p>1 was an Idolater. 2. was the rod of God to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the sinnes of <hi>Ahab,</hi> according as <hi>Baasha</hi> was to <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 15. 29. 3. His seruice thus performed according to Gods Command, was rewarded with establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing his posteritie vpon the Throne of Israel to the fourth generation, Chap. 10. ver. 30. He
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:178475:75"/> raigned 28. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="12">12 <hi>Iehoahaz,</hi> sonne of <hi>Iehu,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> Chapters 10, 13. an Idolater: the <hi>Syrians</hi> preuaile against him, but he is restored. Reigneth 17. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. <hi>Ioash,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Iehoahaz,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 13. 14. an Idolater; warred with <hi>Amaziah.</hi> Raigned 16. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="14">14 <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> the son of <hi>Ioash,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 14. an Idolater, restoreth the Coasts of Israel. Reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned yeeres 41.</p>
                     <p n="15">15 <hi>Zachariah,</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 14. 15. an Idolater, slaine by <hi>Shallum,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:178475:76"/> raigned 6. months.</p>
                     <p n="16">16 <hi>Shallum,</hi> the son of <hi>Iabesh,</hi> Chapt. 15. 15. slaine by <hi>Menahem,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing raigned one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</p>
                     <p n="17">17 <hi>Menahem,</hi> Chap. 15. 14. Idolatrous and cruell, raised a great sūme of money of his people to giue to the King of <hi>Ashur</hi> to depart from him, raigned ten yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="18">18 <hi>Pekahiah,</hi> the Son of <hi>Menahem,</hi> Cha. 15. an Idolater, slaine by his Captaine <hi>Pekah</hi> the son of <hi>Remaliah,</hi> after hee had raigned 2. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="19">19 <hi>Pekah,</hi> Chap. 15. 27.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:178475:76"/> an Idolater, in his time the King of <hi>Ashur</hi> carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth some of <hi>Israel</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. <hi>Hoshea</hi> slayeth <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kah,</hi> after that hee had raigned twenty yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="20">20 <hi>Hoshea</hi> the son of <hi>Elah,</hi> Chapters 15. 17. an Idolater, is treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to <hi>Salmaneser,</hi> who carryed him Captiue in the 9. yeere of his raigne: after that, <hi>Israel</hi> feared o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gods; vsed heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish fashions, and of wicked Kings before him, erected places of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, and performed seruice therein, and reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the Prophets.</p>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:178475:77"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hitherto of all the Kings of <hi>Israel</hi> with their names and condition, till the Captiuitie. The Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in like manner, frō <hi>Iehoshaphat,</hi> to <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> according as they are set downe in this booke, and in the <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6 <hi>Iehoram</hi> or <hi>Ioram</hi> (the Lord is high and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,) to argue the feare of God which his good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iehosaphat</hi> would haue imprinted in him, 2. <hi>Ki.</hi> 8, 16. &amp; 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21. but his actions were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answerable to his name;
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:178475:77"/> for, 1. he married <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah.</hi> Secondly, he was bloody (for hee slew all his brethren, and the Princes of <hi>Israel)</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and idolatrous; and liued without being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired. But the Lord was mighty and exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him; for hee made the <hi>Edomites, Philistims,</hi> and <hi>Arabians</hi> powerfull against him, his wife and children were all slaine, saue onely <hi>Iehoahaz</hi> his yongest son: yet being sencelesse stil of the hand of God, hee sent him a sore disease in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, which afterwards
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:178475:78"/> fell out, after hee had raigned 8. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 <hi>Ahaziah</hi> the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest sonne of <hi>Iehoram,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise called <hi>Ochosias,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> Chapters 8, 9, 10. and 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 22. an Idolater, corrupted by <hi>Athaliah</hi> his wicked mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and her friends; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to warre with <hi>Ioram</hi> the son of <hi>Ahab</hi> against <hi>Hazael, Iehoram</hi> beeing wounded, <hi>Ahaziah</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to see him, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with him against <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu,</hi> to the destruction of himselfe, and all that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained to him, and raigned one yeere.</p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:178475:78"/>
                     <p n="8"> 8 <hi>Athaliah</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> and daughter of <hi>Omri,</hi> 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> Chapters 22, 23. and 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11. an idolatrous woman, and a vsurper of the Crowne of <hi>Iudah,</hi> who when <hi>Ahaziah</hi> was slaine, killed all the kings seed, saue only <hi>Ioash</hi> that was reserued by <hi>Iehosha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beath</hi> his Aunt, sister to <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> and was kept 6. y. in the house of the Lord, &amp; by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the priest was made King, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaliah</hi> slaine, after shee had raigned 7. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="9">9 <hi>Ioash,</hi> son of <hi>Ahazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi>
                        <pb n="138" facs="tcp:178475:79"/> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 24. and 2. <hi>King.</hi> 12. whose actions are distinguished either good or bad, according to seuerall times.</p>
                     <p>First, good, so long as <hi>Iehoiada</hi> a faithful Priest and prudent counsellour liued, when as there was commandement for the repayring of the Temple that was broken downe by <hi>Athaliah,</hi> and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēts for seruice of God prouided therein, colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Leuits at the charge of the people.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, euill, after the death of <hi>Iehoiada,</hi> when with the Princes
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:178475:79"/> he left the care of Gods house, and respect of the Prophets, worshipped I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, and gaue comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to kill <hi>Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> the sonne of <hi>Iehoiada,</hi> whose death the Lord required (according to his prayer) by sending the <hi>Aramites</hi> vpon those Princes, and his owne seruants that slew <hi>Ioash</hi> their King.</p>
                     <p n="10">10 <hi>Amaziah,</hi> the son of <hi>Ioash,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 14. and 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 25. vpright, but not perfect, numbreth many thousands of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> &amp; hired many of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> but these were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missed
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:178475:80"/> by him at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of a man of God. Vpon the victory he had ouer the <hi>Edomites,</hi> hee worshipped the strange gods hee found among them. <hi>Ioash</hi> out-braueth him in termes, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards brought him to <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> whose wals he brake down, and ransac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the Temple, and the Kings house; and was afterwards slaine, hauing raigned 29. yeeres.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Here note, that these 4. last named, <hi>Ahaziah, Athaliah, Ioash,</hi> and <hi>Amaziah,</hi> are not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi>
                           <pb n="141" facs="tcp:178475:80"/> Chap. 1. in <hi>CHRISTS</hi> Genealogie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="11">11 <hi>Azariah</hi> (God hath helped me) or <hi>Vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia,</hi> (the LORD is my strength) called also <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia,</hi> and <hi>Ozia,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Amaziah,</hi> Cha. 15. &amp; 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26. by all the said appellations wished his son the assistance of God: where, of the acts of him performed, and effects answerable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                     <p>First, of his well-doing in the dayes of <hi>Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah;</hi> the effect, he prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in estate, was victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in warres against the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:178475:81"/>
                        <hi>Philistims;</hi> grew famous in the world, was strong in munition, and had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny valiant Souldiers.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Was proud in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, &amp; tooke vpon him the Priests office; &amp; was in conclusion a Leper, &amp; cut off from the house of GOD, and raigned 52. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="12">12 <hi>Iotham,</hi> Chap. 15. and 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 27. (The Lord is vpright and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.) In lieu of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to God for his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers victories, and for his encouragement to serue him, yet the high places stood. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:178475:81"/> of his seruice of God were, he preuailed against the <hi>Ammonits;</hi> he built much, and amongst other things, the gate of the Temple, called <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull,</hi> and raigned 16. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="13">13 <hi>Ahaz,</hi> the son of <hi>Iotham,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. and 2. <hi>King.</hi> 16. (apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or possessing) to wit of such possessions as he had left him: but the is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue was not answerable to his name, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of his sinnes: his sins were first, Idolatry, second, hardnes of heart, which was a great sinne
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:178475:82"/> in him, and likewise a punishment of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer sinne; the more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy the hand of God was vpon him, the worse he euer shewed himselfe. The iudgements accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying his sin, were mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titudes of enemies; <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, Israelites, Edomites, Philistims;</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Ashur</hi> in whom hee trusted, playd false with him, he raigned 16 yeers.</p>
                     <p n="14">14 <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> Chap. 18, 19, 20. and 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 29. &amp; 30, 31, 32. (yy strength is the Lord.) The father praying for his sonnes better successe
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:178475:82"/> against his enemies then he had himselfe; and the successe was in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects according to his name, in that God gaue him strength.</p>
                     <p>First, to set open the Temple of God which before was shut, and to purge out the corruption in religion, and to insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the Passeouer.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, to giue the proud insulting <hi>Assyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> the ouerthrow.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, to recouer of his disease, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long his life 15. yeeres, the same confirmed by the Sunne retrogradate,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:178475:83"/> or going backe tenne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in <hi>Ahaz</hi> his Sun-Diall. Hee raigned 29. yeeres. In stead of thāks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing to God, he glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his wealth.</p>
                     <p n="15">15 <hi>Manasses,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. <hi>(For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull)</hi> because his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had forgotten his troubles after he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from his great sicknesse. The like, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. 51. Secondly, to teach his son to forget the superstition of his fore-fathers: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywise, hee establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in the highest na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: the sequell where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:178475:83"/> was either in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or in mercy.</p>
                     <p>First for his sinne, hee was the first King of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> that was carried Captiue out of his owne Land.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Vpon his his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his sinne, he was released, and sent backe into his owne Country, and was zealous for God and his truth. Hee raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 55. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="16">16 <hi>Amon,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. <hi>(Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed)</hi> In Idolatry, by the appointment of <hi>Manas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> his father, sinned like
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:178475:84"/> him, but did not repent as he did; hee was slaine by his owne seruants in his owne house, after he had raigned 2. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="17">17 <hi>Iosias,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 22. and 23. and 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> Chapters 34, 35. (The Lord is a fire:) but not as his father thought that God should assist his sonne, if he persiisted in Idolatry like his father; but the fire of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was in him, indeede the manifestation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. First; by pulling downe superstition and Idolatry and Idolatrous places. Secondly, in the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:178475:84"/> defence of true Religiō, by repayring the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, causing the Law of God to be read, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining the Passeouer.</p>
                     <p>The most noted sin of <hi>Iosias,</hi> was rashnesse in warring against <hi>Pharaoh Necho,</hi> in fauour of the <hi>Assyrians</hi> that had been kinde to his grandfather <hi>Manasses,</hi> as is most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. Hee raigned 31. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="18">18 <hi>Iehoahaz</hi> or <hi>Iohanan,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 23. and 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 36. the sonne of <hi>Iosias,</hi> displaced by the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> after he had raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 3. moneths, wicked
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:178475:85"/> as his fathers.</p>
                     <p n="19">19 <hi>Eliakim,</hi> so called by <hi>Iosias,</hi> (My strong God will raise vp) called afterwards by <hi>Pharaoh Necho, Iehoiakim,</hi> (The Lord will raise vp) writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten somtimes <hi>Iakim.</hi> Of him, reade <hi>Ieremie,</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 22, 26, 36. where his sinnes and punishments are recorded. Hee raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 11. yeeres.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. <hi>Iehoiachin,</hi> or <hi>Ieco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah,</hi> or <hi>Coniah,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. in sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, <hi>(The Lord wil make ready) viz.</hi> to Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, although they beleeued it not at the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:178475:85"/> preaching of <hi>Ieremie.</hi> He deliuered himselfe into the hāds of <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> &amp; afterwards, both hee and his wiues; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and men of actiuity, together with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel,</hi> were carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Babel,</hi> after hee had raigned three moneths and ten daies.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> or <hi>Matat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Captiuity.</note> so called by the King of <hi>Babel,</hi> hee is called <hi>Ieconiahs</hi> brother 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 36. 10. but 1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 3. 16. he is called <hi>Ieconi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> son; which is not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally to bee vnderstood, for <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was not his
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:178475:86"/> sonne naturally but his Vncle, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 24. 17. his sinnes and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are to bee consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. An Idolater, as were his fore-fathers.</item>
                        <item>2. Of obdurate heart and incorrigible.</item>
                        <item>3. Falsified his Oath made to <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>His punishment.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The chiefe Priests and the people were bad like himselfe, and they both mocked and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Messengers and Prophets of God sent to admonish them.</p>
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:178475:86"/>
                     <p n="2">2. The incursion of cruell and implacable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, that put out the eyes of the King, after they had slaine his sons before his eyes, bound him in chaines, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him to <hi>Babel;</hi> the particulars of that Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 25. He reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eleuen yeeres.</p>
                     <trailer>Hitherto at large of the Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> ioyntly and seueral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; hereafter briefely of their seuerall captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and degrees of the same.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>The Captiuitie of this
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:178475:87"/> people, is noted in a three-fold consideration of time, either</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Past, when they were in Egypt, <hi>Exodus</hi> the first, to the fourteenth Chapter.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Then to come by the Romanes, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test persecutors, both by ciuill gouernment of their Emperours, and hierarchy of Popes.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Present, when the Iewes were captiues to the Babylonians, by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar,</hi> of <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> of <hi>Chams</hi> house; and the same either fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned by <hi>Moses, Deut.</hi>
                        <pb n="155" facs="tcp:178475:87"/> 28. 64. &amp;c. and by most of the Prophets, or now executed vpon <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> and that either partially in the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Estate of</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Israel,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Pekah,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 15. 25. of <hi>Iehoahaz,</hi> 2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 13. 3. In the hand of <hi>Hazael</hi> and <hi>Benhadad</hi> Kings of <hi>Aram.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Totally.</p>
                     <p>In the dayes of <hi>Hoshea,</hi> that was carried captiue into <hi>Ashur,</hi> in the sixt yere of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 18. 10, 11.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Of <hi>Iudah,</hi> 1. partially in the raigne of <hi>Amasiah,</hi>
                        <pb n="156" facs="tcp:178475:88"/> when <hi>Ioash</hi> entred Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, 2. <hi>Chron</hi> 25. 23. of <hi>Manasses,</hi> as in the tytle of <hi>Manasses.</hi> Of <hi>Iehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim,</hi> seruant to <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 24. 2. Totally, in the dayes of <hi>Iekoniah</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> as is before noted.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="1 Chronicles" type="book">
                  <head>1. Chronicles.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHronicles,</hi> or words of Dayes, or of Time wherein the memorable Acts were performed in the Common-wealth of Gods people:</p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:178475:88"/>
                  <p>Or, PARALIPOMEN, of things omitted in the books of the <hi>Kings</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Esdras,</hi> returned to <hi>Ierusalem</hi> after the Captiuitie of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Chronicles</hi> intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the Kingdome of <hi>Israel,</hi> deriuing it from particular persons and heads, mediate or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate. 1. From <hi>Adam,</hi> so as Christ came, &amp; is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued as wel from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before the Floud, as after; and so hath euer beene the teacher of the Church, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the end of the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:178475:89"/> world. Secondly, from <hi>Iacob,</hi> in their 12. Tribes, and that vnder the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of <hi>Saul,</hi> Chap. 9, 10. And <hi>Dauid,</hi> from the eleuenth to the end. The Totall of all which, is about the number of two thousand, nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, eightie and fiue yeeres.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2 Chronicles" type="book">
                  <head>2. Chronicles.</head>
                  <p>OF the increase of the Kingdome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Salomon,</hi> to the tenth Chapter, and the decrease therof in Kings
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:178475:89"/> succeeding, particularly laid down before, to the yeere of the Returne frō Captiuitie, mentioned in the Conclusion of this book, containing yeeres 472.</p>
                  <trailer>Hitherto of the fift Age, <note place="margin">The sixt Age.</note> The sixt followeth, from the Captiuitie of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> to the re-edifying of the Temple and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem, (after which all prophecying fayled) containing yeeres 143.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="Ezra, Nehemiah" type="books">
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:178475:90"/>
                  <head>EZRA, &amp; NEHEMIAH.</head>
                  <p>SO as the estate of the Iewes is hereafter to be considered, either in <hi>Babylon,</hi> or in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. The former, in the booke of <hi>Ester,</hi> and the latter in the books more immediately following, which are generally cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the first and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Esdras,</hi> but of others <hi>Ezra,</hi> and <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> in which wee are
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:178475:90"/> to obserue, concerning persons and actions.</p>
                  <p>Persons, are either such as returned from Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie; or that procured the same.</p>
                  <p>Persons returning, are considered generally and in grosse, or specially.</p>
                  <p>The totall, were two and forty thousand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides their seruants and Maids, <hi>Ezra</hi> 2. 65. Of whom some are set downe in his booke of <hi>Ezra,</hi> the rest in the bookes following.</p>
                  <p>The parties among them of speciall note were,</p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:178475:91"/>
                  <p>First, <hi>Zorobabel</hi> their Prince or Gouernour, (because there were none called Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> after the Captiuitie) hee was descended from <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ieshua</hi> the Priest.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ezra</hi> a Scribe, prompt in the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> Chap. 7. 6. descended of <hi>Aaron;</hi> in great fauour with <hi>Cyrus</hi> K. of <hi>Persia,</hi> with the people of the Iewes, and with Gods: of him the booke hath it name, because of his carefulnesse to further the worke of God.</p>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:178475:91"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> highly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of <hi>Darius,</hi> the Vnkle of <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Daniel</hi> a Prophet, and so esteemed so long as that Common-wealth lasted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mordecai</hi> a Iew, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried captiue with <hi>Ieco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah, Hest.</hi> 2. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hester,</hi> in high esteeme with <hi>Ahasuerosh, Hest.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
                  <p>Persons by whom they were returned, were</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Persia,</hi> of the house of <hi>Sem,</hi> in the first yeere of his Raigne, answering to the 70. yeere of the Captiuitie,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:178475:92"/> according to <hi>Ieremies</hi> Prophecie, Chap. 25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Darius,</hi> of the <hi>Medes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended of <hi>Iaphet, Neh.</hi> 2. by whom the house of God was commanded to be finished in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond yeere of his Raigne though the <hi>Israelites</hi> that were in <hi>Samaria</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The matter in both these Bookes contained, is consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the seuerall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and imployments of the said persons; &amp; the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that God gaue by thē.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> to build the Temple. <hi>Ezra,</hi> to plant Religion, Chapters 3, 4,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:178475:92"/> 5, 6. and for the commō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, Chapters 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> to build their wals, Chapters 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the Law of God to bee put in execution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, from thence to the end of <hi>Nehemiah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The effect, in that the businesse was furthered by the goodnes of God.</p>
                  <p>First, mouing <hi>Cyrus</hi> to set forwards this worke, Chap. 1. by giuing them leaue to go to <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> commanding others to relieue them, and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing what <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> had carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:178475:93"/> and by a decree for the effecting of the same, Chap. 6.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, By stirring vp <hi>Darius,</hi> who granted his Letters to <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> for prouision to build the Palace and the wals, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Inclyning the heart of the Prince, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and people to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the work, &amp; by dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointing the enemies, <hi>Ezra</hi> Chapters 4, 5. and <hi>Nehem.</hi> Chapters 4, 5, 6. so that this Temple had more spirituall ornamēts then the first, because all nations of the earth came
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:178475:93"/> vnto it, and CHRIST taught therein. And here endeth the glory of the <hi>Babylonians:</hi> &amp; now <hi>Iaphet</hi> is perswaded to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Sem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Esther" type="book">
                  <head>ESTER.</head>
                  <p>THis Booke hath it name of her, and she standeth in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation either to <hi>Assuerus,</hi> or to her kindred and people.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To <hi>Ahashuerosh,</hi> that was called <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi>
                     <pb n="168" facs="tcp:178475:94"/> which was the common name of al Kings of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia;</hi> or <hi>Darius</hi> that raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned twelue yeeres after <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and in the third yeere of his raigne, the story of <hi>Ester</hi> began, who was married to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> in the seuenth yeere of his gouernment.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to her kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and people of the Iewes, for whose good, first, shee aduentured her life, Chap. 4. endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Chap. 3. &amp; 4. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, procured their welfare; first, by pulling downe their enemies, principally as <hi>Haman,</hi> &amp;
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:178475:94"/> his Complices, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 7, 9. Secondly, by aduancing her friends, and they either princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, as <hi>Mordechai,</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 2, 6, 8 10. the suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed author of this booke.</p>
                  <p>Or genrally, as all the <hi>Iewes;</hi> so as this booke containeth things done vnder <hi>Ahashuerosh,</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi> in exile vnder the <hi>Persians, Medes, Assyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Chaldeans.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>Hitherto of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior Prophets; the Hagriographa or sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred writings doe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="Job" type="book">
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:178475:95"/>
                  <head>IOB.</head>
                  <p>IN this booke, we may obserue the time wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Iob</hi> liued, and the manner of his life.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 He liued (as most do coniecture) in the time of the Israelites being in Aegypt, as the names of his friends doe import, conferring them with <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. 21. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Historie is most proper to the third Age.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the course of his life, note his humiliatiō
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:178475:95"/> and exaltation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That beeing a very godly man, and rich, was notwithstanding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards afflicted both in body and minde; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the losse of goods, seruants, and children, Chap. 1. was tempted by his Wife, Chap. 2. disquieted in his minde by Satan, Chap. 6. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued by his friends of hypocrisie generally throughout the whole Booke.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His exaltation, wherein, of the manner precedent &amp; consequēt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In <hi>Iobs</hi> Confession
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:178475:96"/> of his error to GOD, Chapters 39. 42.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By God himselfe, who 1. pleadeth his cause, Chap. 42.</p>
                  <p>2 Restoreth him riches double to that hee had; so as this Story is Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: Sorrowes Ioy.</p>
                  <p>Marke the iust man, the end of him is Peace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Psalms" type="book">
                  <head>PSALMES.</head>
                  <p>A Psalme is properly taken for a Song or Hymne that is deliuered on a tunable Instrumēt; wherein are to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, <hi>The Dittie, Tune, and the Singers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Dittie or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:178475:96"/> of the Psalmes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth for the most part, of Prayer and Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing; fitting euery ones occasion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly, the tune or manner of setting it downe; full of delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by musicall notes, wherewith mans nature is much delighted, as the seuerall Titles do shewe; &amp; there are some called Songs of degrees, as <hi>Psal.</hi> 120. to 134. in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 15. which name they had, in likelihood, because they were sung at their going vp the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:178475:97"/> Staires of the Temple, whereof there were fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene steppes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The Singers are principall, or subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; first, <hi>Dauid,</hi> called by a certaine excellency, <hi>The sweet Singer of</hi> Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 1. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, other godly men, as they are entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of <hi>Ethan, Psal.</hi> 89. of <hi>Salomon, Psal.</hi> 71. of <hi>Moses, Psal.</hi> 90. and so of other; and of all that haue <hi>Dauids</hi> spirit, the duty commanded, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5. 19. and practised by the godly in seuerall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages in ancient time,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:178475:97"/> and shall be the exercise of the Saints in heauen, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Proverbs" type="book">
                  <head>PROVERBS.</head>
                  <p>A Prouerbe is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legant manner of speech, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending much matter in small roome.</p>
                  <p>In these Prouerbs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue, who wrote them, the time whē they were written; and the subiect matter of the writing.</p>
                  <p>First &amp; principall was <hi>Salomon</hi> the Son of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
                     <pb n="176" facs="tcp:178475:98"/> whereof they haue the name: then other worthy men, the follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers of that good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> as appeareth in the inscription of the 25. Chapter, and of <hi>Agur,</hi> Chap. 30.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death; after his fall, and vpon his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, concerning God or man; of GOD, touching such things as wee ought to embrace, Chapters 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 9. what we must beware of Chapters 5, 7. the secōd part is morall, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:178475:98"/> in seuerall duties of piety and humanity to be performed towards man in the course of life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Ecclesiastes" type="book">
                  <head>Ecclesiastes, <hi>or the</hi> PREACHER.</head>
                  <p>WHEREIN wee may see, that after all our carke &amp; care where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we spend our time in this troublesome world, nothing remaineth in the reckoning, but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vexation of spirit, instanced in the enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:178475:99"/> of particulars, of such things as the vaine world thinketh felicity to consist in, whereof <hi>Salomon</hi> had experience in the fruitiō of the best, Chapters 1, 2. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth from his obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of other mens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours, the misery of all, Chapters 3. to the 10. And therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth the point; That he is the only hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py man, that feareth God, and keepeth his Commandements.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Canticles (Song of Solomon)" type="book">
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:178475:99"/>
                  <head>Canticles, <hi>or Song of</hi> Salomon.</head>
                  <p>WHEREIN,
<list>
                        <item>1. Of whom it was made.</item>
                        <item>2. The matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it consisteth.</item>
                        <item>3 Of mutuall affection of the parties.</item>
                        <item>And 4 Of the happy consummation of all.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 The parties interes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed herein, are Christ the head of the Church, and euery faithfull soule.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The matter, is of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communion and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie betweene them
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:178475:100"/> both set forth vnder the figure of a marriage, in which Christ is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the bridegroome, and the Church (which is but one) to the bride.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 This league is made vp, and set forth in the mutuall affection either to other, made knowne by seuerall comparisons, first, of Christ and the Church ioyntly, Chap. 1. Of the Church and Christ, Chap. 2. he to a Tree, she to a Lillie and Rose, in many compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Christ made to the Church, Chap. 4. &amp; the Church to him, c. 5.</p>
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:178475:100"/>
                  <p n="4">4 The making vp the match and conclusion of the same: that, in this life; this, in the life to come: and the same confirmed by certaine pawnes and pledges, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; receiued as loue-tokens betweene them both.</p>
                  <p>That which Christ hath giuen, is his Spirit within vs, which he hath sent vnto vs, and the Looking glasses of his Word and Sacraments left among vs.</p>
                  <p>The pledge or earnest that he hath taken of vs, is our nature, assumed
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:178475:101"/> into the person of the Godhead, and hath car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it vp with him into heauen: and vvhen the Roomes and Mansions there are prepared, hee will come againe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously for his Spouse.</p>
                  <trailer>Hitherto of the Hagio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapha: the latter Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets doe follow to bee intreated of.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Introduction</hi> to the reading of the PROPHETS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PRophets,</hi> were persons called of God to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:178475:101"/> and expound vnto men the will of GOD, concerning things either present or to come.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of Prophets, some were only in act, but not in Office, and so <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; some other that pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the sacred hymnes by the motion of Gods Spirit, without any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted change in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward gesture. 2. In act and Office, as were the Reuelations, manifested to the holy Prophets, Pen-men of a great part of the Scriptures; such as <hi>Esay, Ieremy,</hi> and the rest, either in dreames, or
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:178475:102"/> wake, but in extasie; in which manner we are to vnderstand all, or most of them, that are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after mentioned.</p>
                  <p>The doctrine of the Prophets serueth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct, reprehend and to comfort; which order is generally obserued by all, or most of them.</p>
                  <p>Touching these, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the manner how their doctrine came first to be published; &amp; then of the Prophets, and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of their seuerall prophecies.</p>
                  <p>The summe of their doctrine was first set vpō
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:178475:102"/> the Temple doore for certaine dayes, and the Priests tooke it downe, and reserued it among the Registers, <hi>Isay</hi> 8. 1. 2. and <hi>Habakkuk</hi> 2. 2.</p>
                  <p>As for the time wherein all of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied, is hard to bee gathered, but for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction, so farre as is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, or probable, wee say, that some of them were onely before the Captiuitie; some in the Captiuitie, and others after that the same was expired; the particulars wherof hereafter follow in their seuerall places</p>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:178475:103"/>
                  <p>Those that do follow, are called the posteriour Prophets, because they prophecied of many things that should come to passe to the comming of Christ; and of some things afterwards, as in <hi>Daniel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And of these, some are called the greater Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; as <hi>Isay, Ieremie, Ezekiel, Daniel;</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the lesser, as all that came after them. In the setting downe whereof, all or most of these cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, are briefely deliuered.</p>
                  <p>1. What they were.
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:178475:103"/> 2. When they vvere. 3. Vnder what Kings raigne. 4. What was the effect of their seuerall prophecies. 5. What followed therevpon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Isaiah" type="book">
                  <head>ISAIAH.</head>
                  <p>THe sonne of <hi>Amos,</hi> an Euangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet setting forth many things of Christ, and by him interpreted, <hi>Luke</hi> 4. and by others, as by <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip, Act.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Prophecied as is coniectured in the yeere of the world, 3198. and continued a Prophet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 64. yeeres.</p>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:178475:104"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Prophesied in the dayes of <hi>Vzziah, Iotham, Ahaz,</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> So as hee was before the Captiuitie.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. His message was directed to <hi>Iudah</hi> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally; the Tenour wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is a Denunciation, and Consolation. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation, first against Gods people, from the 1. chap. to the 11. 2. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their enemies, frō the 13. chap. to 24. The Consolation, is in regard of a Temporall or Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall deliuerance. 1. By <hi>Cyrus,</hi> c. 45. 1. Secondly, To the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> by the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:178475:104"/> cōming of Christ, cha. 9.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The effect, in respect of himself, was to be put to death by <hi>Manasses.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Jeremiah" type="book">
                  <head>IEREMIE.</head>
                  <p>FIrst, the sonne of <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> born in <hi>Anathoth</hi> a Citie within 3. miles of <hi>Ierusalem;</hi> began to prophecie in <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> about the yeere of the Creation, 3316. and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied about 40. yeres.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Prophecied in the daies of <hi>Iosiah,</hi> beginning in the 13. yeere of his raigne, and in the dayes of <hi>Iehoiakim,</hi> &amp; <hi>Zedekiah;</hi> so as he was in the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:178475:105"/> of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. His prophecie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth a fearefull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Gods Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Captiuitie, with the Reasons &amp; sins procuring it, as in seueral Chapters may be seene: his message was princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally directed to the Iewes, in <hi>Iudea,</hi> vnder se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Kings thereof, to Chap. 42; Or in Egypt, with the destruction of their enemies fore-told.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, addeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation, in assuring them in diuers places of their returne from Captiuitie; From chap. 29.</p>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:178475:105"/>
                  <p n="4">4. He is cast into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for prophecying the truth, and is basely vsed, Chapters 32. 37, 38.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Lamentations" type="book">
                  <head>LAMENTATION,</head>
                  <p>FOr the destruction of their Kingdome, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by <hi>Moses, Deut.</hi> 28. 64. &amp;c. and now exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Ezekiel" type="book">
                  <head>EZEKIEL. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>THe sonne of <hi>Buzi</hi> in <hi>Caldaea,</hi> where hee prophecied the same things that <hi>Ieremy</hi> did in <hi>Iudaea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Began his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, about the yeere of
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:178475:106"/> the creation, 3350. in the fift yeere of <hi>Iehoiachins</hi> captiuitie.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Intreateth of the sinnes of the Iewes, as of Idolatry, murdering of the Prophets, oppressing the Stranger, prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sabbath, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sension, Incest, Briberie, Vsury and Extortion, from chap. 20. to 37. for which they were carried captiue: and of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Chap. 37. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied likewise against other Nations, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in the misery of the Iewes. From chap. 25. to 33.</p>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:178475:106"/>
                  <p n="4"> 4. Disobedience of the people to the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, chap. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Daniel" type="book">
                  <head>DANIEL.</head>
                  <p>FIrst, a captiue Iew car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away into <hi>Babel,</hi> in the third yeere of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiakim</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> about the yeere 3340.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hee liued in the dayes of <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar, Belshazzar, Darius,</hi> and <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Prophecyeth of the succeeding estate of the world to the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the change of gouernment, considered
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:178475:107"/> in foure Monarchies, and resemblances thereof, in the opinion of some: 1. the Babylonians to gold; Chap. 2. 32. the <hi>Persian,</hi> to Siluer; the <hi>Grecian,</hi> to Brasse; the <hi>Romane,</hi> as some vnderstand, Chap. 2. 40. to Iron and Clay: which others interpret of the declining Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> kindred, and the miserable estate of the Iewes in that decaying Empire by the <hi>Syrians,</hi> and <hi>Egyptians:</hi> Insomuch as they called their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by such names as shewed the desires of
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:178475:107"/> their hearts for a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sauiour, that might defend them. And in this sence the Apostles might aske Christ the question, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 6. Lord, wilt thou at this time restore again the Kingdome to <hi>Israel?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. For his constancie in seruing God, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saking Idolatry, he is cast into a denne of Lyons, Chap. 6. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Hosea" type="book">
                  <head>HOSEAH.</head>
                  <p>FIrst, the son of <hi>Beeri,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Concerning the time, it was before the Captiuitie, like as the Prophet <hi>Isay,</hi> in the daies
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:178475:108"/> of <hi>Vzziah, Iotham, Ahaz,</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and in the dayes of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the sonne of <hi>Ioosh</hi> King of <hi>Israel:</hi> with this difference, that <hi>Esays</hi> prophecy concernd <hi>Iuda</hi> principally; and <hi>Hoseas, Israel</hi> in the top of their prosperitie, when they thought themselues in Gods fauour.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To tell them of their sinnes, as of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Chap. 1. Want of knowledge, (the cause of all manner of other sinnes) chap. 4. 6. surfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the King, chap. 7. flatterie in the people.
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:178475:108"/> For which, and other of their sinnes, they are threatened to haue their Kingdome taken from them by the <hi>Assyrians,</hi> Chap. 11. vsing conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation afterwards, if they did amend.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Continuance in their sins to their after-destruction: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing that <hi>Hoseah</hi> had beene their Prophet 70. yeeres.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Joel" type="book">
                  <head>IOEL.</head>
                  <p>FIrst, the sonne of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuel,</hi> most likely to be about the time of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="198" facs="tcp:178475:109"/>
                  <p n="2"> 2. Hee prophecied to <hi>Iuda.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 His exhortation is to repentance, and that for their sinnes of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and surfetting, or else, that they were to expect, First, extreme plague of famine. 2. If they repented not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, to looke for the sword of the King of <hi>Ashur.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Amos" type="book">
                  <head>AMOS.</head>
                  <p>FIrst, The sonne of a poore Heards-man, borne in <hi>Tecoa,</hi> a Towne of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 He prophesieth; first,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:178475:109"/> against the Gentiles, cha. 1. then against the Iewes and Israelites. His argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is drawn from the lesse to the greater. If God punished those that had little or no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, then, much more those that sinned vpon knowledge. The sinnes are taxed from the 2. Chapter to the 9. The sinnes are, Cruelty, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, Securitie, lacke of pittie, hoording vp of Corne, and Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Obadiah" type="book">
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:178475:110"/>
                  <head>OBADIAH.</head>
                  <p>THere is little obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of his time or Kindred: but by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of places, <hi>Ieremie</hi> 49. <hi>&amp; Ezek.</hi> 25. it is most like, he liued in the time of both their Prophesies.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The Contents, hee comforteth the Israelites now in great miserie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their brethren, the <hi>Idumeans,</hi> who came of <hi>Esau,</hi> that were great enemies vnto them, and reioyced in the spoyles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Jonah" type="book">
                  <head>IONAH:</head>
                  <p>FIrst, The sonne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittaj,</hi> borne in <hi>Gath</hi>
                     <pb n="201" facs="tcp:178475:110"/>
                     <hi>Heper,</hi> a Towne in <hi>Zabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> he liued in or about the time of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the sonne of <hi>Ioash.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 He prefigureth the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the Gentiles, sent for the conuersion of <hi>Niniueh,</hi> the chiefe Citie of the <hi>Assyrians,</hi> by 3. daies preaching; to conuince Israel, to which hee had preached many yeeres. 3. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, the Citie was spared, and the Prophet complaineth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Micah" type="book">
                  <head>MICAH:</head>
                  <p>BOrne in a Towne that appertayned to
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:178475:111"/>
                     <hi>Beniamin,</hi> but was origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of <hi>Gath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 Hee prophecieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Iudah</hi> in the daies of <hi>Iotham, Ahaz,</hi> &amp; <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> and so of Israel, Chap. 1. 1. for the space of 30. yeeres or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The parties reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, are Princes, Chap. 3. Rich Merchants, cha. 6. corrupt Iudges, chap. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Nahum" type="book">
                  <head>NAHVM.</head>
                  <p>THe parentage of this Prophet is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, nor the time of his prophecie, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectured
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:178475:111"/> to bee in the dayes of <hi>Iotham.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The argument, hee teacheth them of <hi>Iudah</hi> to be ware of reuolting from God, by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Niniuits,</hi> that were afterwards for the same cause destroyed by the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> about 115. yeeres after the former Prophecie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Habakkuk" type="book">
                  <head>HABAKKVK.</head>
                  <p>IT is most like that hee liued about the end of <hi>Iosiahs</hi> raigne, or after.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Hee preacheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the pride and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi>
                     <pb n="204" facs="tcp:178475:112"/> puft vp with their spoils, who were afterwards destroyed by the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Zephaniah" type="book">
                  <head>ZEPHANY.</head>
                  <p>THE sonne of <hi>Cushi,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Iosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> hee foretelleth the Captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and comforteth the godly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Haggai" type="book">
                  <head>HAGGAI.</head>
                  <p>HE and the two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets following, were after the Captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>Haggaj</hi> comforteth the people, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth them to build the
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:178475:112"/> Temple, wherein some were slacke, but forward to build their owne house: he prophesied in the second yeere, and sixt moneth of King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="Zechariah" type="book">
                  <head>ZACHARIAH.</head>
                  <p>HE prophesieth in the eight month of the second yeere of King <hi>Darius.</hi> Hee instructeth the people to auoyd the sinnes of their fathers, &amp; to comfort the people in respect of CHRISTS comming, the manner whereof is described, Chap. 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Malachi" type="book">
                  <pb n="206" facs="tcp:178475:113"/>
                  <head>MALACHIE</head>
                  <p>REproueth abuses and corruptions, now that the Temple was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edifyed, and Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship restored.</p>
                  <trailer>Hitherto of the Prophets and rebuilding of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> and the second Temple, from whence the sacred Scriptures for story do cease. And frō which time, as some doe reckon; vnto the comming of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> are yeeres 483. which is the time of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth age.</trailer>
                  <trailer>Hitherto of the Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The New follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="new" type="testament">
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:178475:113"/>
               <head>THE NEVV TESTAMENT.</head>
               <p>BOTH the Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are but one in substāce, though different in name.</p>
               <p>The substance of them both, is Christ, who as he is <hi>Alpha</hi> &amp; <hi>Omega,</hi> the first and the last, and the same for euer; so the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and merit of his suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings are not bounden within the time of his Incarnation: but the
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:178475:114"/> Testaments are distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished in <hi>the Letter</hi> &amp; <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>Reuelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 The former, called <hi>Old,</hi> in regard of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of Christ to come; the other <hi>New,</hi> wherein the same were fulfilled by Christ exhibited.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That whereas the Old was deliuered in Types, Shaddowes, and Ceremonies; in this, Christ is plainely &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly made knowne: otherwise, as the faces of the Cherubims were one towards another, and both towards the Mercy-seate: so both
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:178475:114"/> these Testaments beare witnesse one to another, and both looke vpon Christ.</p>
               <p>In the old Testament there is the occultation of the New; and in the New Testament, is the manifestation of the old.</p>
               <p>In the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment obserue, how the matter therein is sorted, and how Christ is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
               <p>The matter, is either Legall, as of the foure Euangelists: or Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, as the Acts of the Apostles; doctrinall, as the Epistles: or Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:178475:115"/> as the Apocalypse.</p>
               <p>The manner of Christ propounded therein, is set down diuersly; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in obserue how the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelists doe varie, and wherein they agree.</p>
               <div n="gospels" type="part">
                  <p n="1">1 The former: In that some of them principally intended to set downe the Manhood of Christ, others the Life of <hi>Christ,</hi> others his Diuinity.</p>
                  <p>The humanity of Christ is most cleerely expressed by <hi>Mathew,</hi> Chap. 1. 1. The Booke of the generation of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ the Sonne of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and by <hi>Luke,</hi>
                     <pb n="211" facs="tcp:178475:115"/> Chap. 3. 23. with this note of difference, that <hi>Luke</hi> deriueth Christ vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to <hi>Adam,</hi> vers. 38. but <hi>Mathew</hi> downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from <hi>Abraham: Luke</hi> followeth his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall line without menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any of them in <hi>Mathew,</hi> besides <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiel</hi> and <hi>Zerubabbel,</hi> ver. 27. <hi>Mathew</hi> bringeth Christ to be the heire of <hi>Dauids</hi> throne, by a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall succession from <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Marke</hi> setteth down the life of Christ, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with <hi>Iohn Baptist.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 S. <hi>Iohn</hi> intreateth of
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:178475:116"/> his Diuinity, Chap. 1. vers. 1, 2, 3. &amp;c. and that especially, because the same was opposed by some heretikes of that time.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them all in some particulers, or in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The former, as first, in the preparation that was made to his manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. and 4. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 3. and 4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The manifestation it selfe, by preaching and Miracles in <hi>Galilee, Mat.</hi> 4. to 19. <hi>Mark.</hi> 1. vnto
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:178475:116"/> the 10. Chap. <hi>Luk.</hi> part of the 3. and 4. Chapter, to the 17.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Of his comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iurie</hi> towards his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, <hi>Math.</hi> 19. 20. <hi>Mark.</hi> 10. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. vnto the 19. S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> is most copious in setting down his Acts it <hi>Iurie,</hi> and hath of the same in <hi>Galilee</hi> about the third Passouer, and after, Chap. 6. to the 12.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Of his Passion at <hi>Ierusalem, Mat.</hi> 21. <hi>Mar.</hi> 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. &amp;c. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The generall here briefly propounded in these words: CHRIST IESVS OVR LORD:
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:178475:117"/> which are heereafter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and is the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of both Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, old and new.</p>
                  <p>Wherein, first briefly and generally obserue the extent of the names of <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular vnfolding of the same and the rest, to make the Testaments compleate.</p>
                  <p>First, the names of <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> are of seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Languages, Greeke and Hebrew, and do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply him to bee Sauiour both of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Rom.</hi> 1. 16.</p>
                  <pb n="215" facs="tcp:178475:117"/>
                  <p>So as neither <hi>Iew</hi> nor <hi>Gentile</hi> haue cause to complaine.</p>
                  <p>Not the <hi>Iew,</hi> because that Christ was borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and sent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; nor the <hi>Gentile,</hi> because Christ was light to them. And <hi>Dauid</hi> the Father of Christ accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the flesh, had much blood from the <hi>Gentiles, Mat.</hi> 1. In a word, Christ took blood of both, and shed it for both.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vnfoulding of Christ consisteth in the signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his names, and
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:178475:118"/> diuine application of the same.</p>
                  <p>First, Christ is a name taken from oyling or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oynting, according to a threefold estate of men of ancient time, Kings, Priests and Prophets.</p>
                  <p>In oyle are considered, fragrancy and agility; the former in relation to sanctification, the latter, to ability in a ready and cheerefull performance of euery Christian and holy duty towards God, or his Image that is in man.</p>
                  <p>First, Christ is anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our King.</p>
                  <pb n="217" facs="tcp:178475:118"/>
                  <p>By the grace of voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, out of the estate of nature; of Sanctification into the life of grace; of glorification, by raysing vp our bodies out of the dust in the resurrection, and by knitting soules &amp; bodies together, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soluing them from sin, and estating vs in perfect glory; which none but this King can doe. And hereto may be referred, whatsoeuer examples are recorded in the sacred Scriptures of this nature.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 CHRIST is our Prophet;</p>
                  <p>And this is deriued
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:178475:119"/> from his Kingly office, and so hath hee manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted himselfe by teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the manner where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is diuers, and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more mediately, or of latter times.</p>
                  <p>The ancient manner of Christs teaching was, first, by his owne voyce from heauen. Secondly, by Angels. Thirdly, by Prophets, in whom his Spirit was long before he came into the world: or, fourthly, by himselfe.</p>
                  <p>The teaching of <hi>Christ</hi> is either personally, or instrumentally to bee considered.</p>
                  <pb n="219" facs="tcp:178475:119"/>
                  <p n="1"> 1. Personally, when hee was vpon the earth, and in different manner, according to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Hearers, to some in Parables; That some might not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand; and that others might more diligently enquire, or better carry away the things taught, and to his preaching, he added Miracles.</p>
                  <p>A <hi>Miracle</hi> is that which surpasseth the power and efficacie of any created nature, but is wrought by God against nature, and the common order of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond causes.</p>
                  <pb n="220" facs="tcp:178475:120"/>
                  <p>Concerning these, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue how they are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced in the Old and New Testament. In the former, they were for the most part destructiue. In the New Testament o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, saue of the <hi>Gadarens,</hi> to punish their ingratitude.</p>
                  <p>The Miracles of Christ were,</p>
                  <p>1. Hee turned Water into Wine; <hi>Io.</hi> 2. 2. Fed 5000. with fiue loaues, <hi>Math.</hi> 14. and 4000. with seuen loaues, <hi>Math.</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He gaue hearing to the Deafe, and speech to the dumbe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 32.</p>
                  <pb n="221" facs="tcp:178475:120"/>
                  <p n="4"> 4. He gaue to the blind their sight, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. as he went out of <hi>Ierusalem;</hi> to two blind men as hee went to <hi>Iericho, Mat.</hi> 20. 29. to one that was born so at <hi>Ierusalem, Ioh.</hi> 9. 1.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He restored the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered hand, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 10.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He healed the man that was lame 38. yeeres, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 5.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He healed the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prosie, <hi>Math.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Palsie, <hi>Math.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. 11.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The Feuer, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1. 31.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The bloudy Issue, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 20. The Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 2.</p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:178475:121"/>
                  <p n="11"> 11. Hee calmed the Seas, beeing in the Ship, <hi>Math.</hi> 8. 29. Walked on the waters, <hi>Math.</hi> 14. 25.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. He raised from the dead the Rulers Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9. the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes sonne, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>Lazarus, Ioh.</hi> 11. 12.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. He deliuered from the possessiō of the diuel, at <hi>Capernaum, Lu.</hi> 35. 4.</p>
                  <p>The reason of all these, for the Confirmation of his doctrine, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sufficiently confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, Miracles haue cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; so as it is miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that men should
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:178475:121"/> not now beleeue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them.</p>
                  <p>Of Christs personall teaching hitherto; now of his teaching by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but in different manner. 1. The Heathen in secular knowledge of Arts &amp; Sciences, which are of God, but of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour nature. 2. Of his people, but in different manner of dispensation thereof, and that either in extraordinarie or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie manner.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of Prophets as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and of Apostles, whereof there were in number twelue, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:178475:122"/> 2, 3. of which <hi>Mathew,</hi> (otherwise called <hi>Leui)</hi> of a Publican was made a Disciple, then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an Apostle, and made an Euangelist, and none but S. <hi>Iohn</hi> and hee had both those Titles.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ordinarie, as Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelists to write; Doctors to teach in some certaine Churches; Pastors to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, and administer the Sacraments; Elders to rule; Deacons to distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute.</p>
                  <p>3. IESVS Christ is our Priest:</p>
                  <p>Yea our Priest and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 9. and our
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:178475:122"/> Passeouer, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 7. who in the fourth Passe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, after he tooke vpon him the ministeriall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, suffered death vpon the Crosse for vs.</p>
                  <p>Wherein first of his <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,</hi> and then of his <hi>Exaltation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. His Humiliation made knowne by his suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, in body or in soule, and then in his birth, life and death.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Borne in <hi>Bethlem, Math.</hi> 2. 1. which place was onely honoured by the birth of Christ and <hi>Dauid.</hi> The time of his birth generally declared.
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:178475:123"/> When the fulnes of time was come, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4. and about the yeere after the Creation, 3963. noted by <hi>Moses, Gen.</hi> 49. 10. Whē the Scepter should depart from <hi>Iudah,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished in <hi>Herod,</hi> complished in <hi>Herod,</hi> who being an <hi>Idumean</hi> of the kindred of <hi>Esau,</hi> had now wrested the Scepter out of <hi>Iudahs</hi> hand, set ouer the Iewes by <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus Caesar,</hi> put downe the <hi>Sanedrim</hi> or 70. Elders of <hi>Iudaea,</hi> and was aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced King of the Iewes.</p>
                  <p>Christs sufferings were either assumed, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed.</p>
                  <pb n="227" facs="tcp:178475:123"/>
                  <p n="1"> 1. Of Christ himselfe, as of GOD to become man, to take the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties incident to our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that were not sinful. Of wearinesse and thirst, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 6, 7. Of hunger and temptation, <hi>Math.</hi> 4. Of feare, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 42.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Imposed by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of some; and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of others.</p>
                  <p>Of the former were <hi>Herod</hi> the King, the high Priest, <hi>Pilate</hi> the Iudge, the Rulers; and their As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistants, the Scribes, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises and the people; and <hi>Iudas</hi> the Traytor.</p>
                  <p>Of the second sort,
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:178475:124"/> were <hi>Peter,</hi> and the rest of the Disciples that went off in his sufferings.</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Herods</hi> there were three.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Herod Ascolonita, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipaters</hi> sonne, whose hand was lifted vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Christ at his birth, and martyred the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Herod Antipas</hi> his sonne, confederate with <hi>Pilate</hi> in Christs death, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23. and killed <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Herod Agrippa,</hi> that killed <hi>Iames,</hi> and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>The malice of the
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:178475:124"/> Iewes towards Christ appeareth in these cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Against the Law, to take away life of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent person by false testimony, and by parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all iudgement, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Against mercy, to deny time of prepared death to him, whom they condemned as a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19. 16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Against ciuilitie, to scoffe at him in his suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, <hi>Mar.</hi> 15, 29. 36. He calleth for <hi>Elias,</hi> and to giue him Vineger calling for drinke, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19. 29.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Against mercy and
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:178475:125"/> iustice, to adde more to his sufferings, then the Law commanded, which was onely to bee cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>Math.</hi> 27. 29. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Christ suffered in Soule</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Combating with his Fathers wrath, feeling the withdrawing of his helpe, and want of the Diuinitie for a while to comfort his humanitie, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 39. to <hi>ver.</hi> 47.</p>
                  <p>And thus the bloud of so many Birds &amp; Beasts shead in the old Law in their seuerall sacrifices, is fulfilled in Christ, who by this means is become ous Iesus, our Physicion,
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:178475:125"/> and our Physicke, sauing vs from the euill of Sin, and of Punishment.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of sinne, by remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it of himselfe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly; or destroying it, in part, by sanctification in this life; wholly, by glory in the life to come.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of punishment, by taking away the sting and venome of it, and by confirming grace and glory.</p>
                  <p>LORD: CHRIST <hi>is</hi> LORD.</p>
                  <p>In his powerfull rising as a King from death, with the conquest of all his enemies. 2. By
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:178475:126"/> his Ascension: Thirdly, Intercession, and fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in that hee shall come the second time in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manner to iudge the world.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The <hi>Resurrection,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a maine Article of Faith, had neede to bee proued, and his abode vpon earth for the space of fortie daies, was very necessary for vs.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Resurrection</hi> is prooued by al the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelists, in the conclusion of all their Gospels, and likewise by many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses of those that saw him after his Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <pb n="233" facs="tcp:178475:126"/>
                  <p>The persons that saw Christ risen, were, <hi>Mary Magdalen, Mark.</hi> 16. 9. both the <hi>Maries, Mat.</hi> 28. 9. two Disciples, <hi>Luk.</hi> 29. 13. <hi>Peter</hi> alone, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 5. all the Disciples together, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Thomas, Ioh.</hi> 20. 19. all the Disciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 16. <hi>Iames,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 his Disciples a fishing, <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 1. the Disciples in the Mount of Oliues, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p>The abode of Christ vpon earth being risen, was necessarie; as to confirme the truth of his Resurrection, so to teach
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:178475:127"/> them in all poynts of Christian Doctrine, and those things that belong to the gouernment of his Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 3.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Ascension, Act.</hi> 1. the manner, in a Cloud: so that we are not now to seeke to know further what is become of him, but must content our selues with that which GOD hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his Word, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Intercession,</hi> which is not meant of any Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers proceeding in some manner of gesture from him on our behalfe, but
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:178475:127"/> the price of his Redēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereon the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looking, is wel plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in him, and with vs in him, <hi>Math.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 His second most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious comming from Heauen in Maiestie with all his holy Angels, whē as he wil reunite the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and soules of his Saints, that they may for euer liue with him in glory, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. vers. 11.</p>
                  <p>CHRIST is (Our) LORD by faith, if we beleeue in him: which faith, the Word begetteth, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments doe confirme,
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:178475:128"/> Hope sustaineth, and Heauen crowneth, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 9.</p>
                  <trailer>The Acts of the Apostles doe follow.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="Acts of the Apostles" type="book">
                  <head>ACTS <hi>of the</hi> APOSTLES.</head>
                  <p>THis Booke is called <hi>The Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> beeing a Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the first Church vnder the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, set down by <hi>Luke,</hi> containing yeeres, about 31. In which, consider vnder what Romane Emperours, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall things were done, spoken of either in this Booke, or in other places
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:178475:128"/> of the New Tastament: and then of the Apostles &amp; their Assistants, as are recorded in this booke.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, in whose times the sacred Story of the New Testament was written, were, 1. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus Caesar,</hi> in whose raigne Christ was born, 2. <hi>Tyberius,</hi> vnder whom he was manifested, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3. and dyed, &amp; persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions grew hot, <hi>Act.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. 3. <hi>Claudius,</hi> vnder whom the Church had some rest, but that <hi>Herod</hi> the deputy King was cruell, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:178475:129"/> 4. <hi>Nero,</hi> vnder whom there was cruell persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which, S. <hi>Paul</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> suffered Martyrdome: and 5. <hi>Domitian,</hi> by whom S. <hi>Iohn</hi> was banisht into <hi>Patmos, Reu.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The number of them is set downe, either ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, as <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 13. with mentiō afterwards of <hi>Mathias,</hi> &amp; of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable calling of <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 1. 1. and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 1. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Particularly, of such Apostles and their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, as are expressed in this booke; as of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                     <pb n="239" facs="tcp:178475:129"/> Chap. 4. <hi>Steuen,</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters 6. 7. <hi>Philip,</hi> Chap. 8. <hi>Saul,</hi> afterward called <hi>Paul,</hi> Chap. 9. &amp;c. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> Chap. 13. <hi>Silas,</hi> Chapters 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16, <hi>Iames,</hi> Chapters 12. 15.</p>
                  <p>All which, are to bee cōsidered, either as they were together before their separation, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 of them all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall at <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> where they were to stay by Christs appointment, Chap. 1. 4. or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, as of <hi>Peter, Iohn,</hi> and others, Chapters, 3, 4, 5. Secondly, after their
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:178475:130"/> separation, and so there is speciall mention of <hi>Paul.</hi> First, with <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> Chapters 13, 14. Secondly, with <hi>Silas,</hi> Chapters 15, 16.</p>
                  <p>The occasion of their separation was two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. First, in regard of the persecution of <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> and so the Church became scattered, Chap. 8. 1. Secondly, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the dissension betweene <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> touching <hi>Iohn, Marke,</hi> which was the Euangelist, Chap. 15. 39.</p>
                  <p>In the separation note the Coūtries into which
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:178475:130"/> the Apostles in seuerall were disperst (as writers report,) and of those as they are set down in this booke.</p>
                  <p>The parts in which the Apostles were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed, are said to be, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> in <hi>Achaia, Iohn</hi> in <hi>Asia, Philip</hi> in <hi>Phrygia, Iames</hi> in <hi>Iurie, Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi> in <hi>Scythia, Thomas</hi> in <hi>India, Mathew</hi> in <hi>Aethiopia, Simon</hi> in <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia, Thaddaeus</hi> in <hi>Meso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potamia,</hi> the other <hi>Iames</hi> in <hi>Spaine, Matthias</hi> in <hi>Palestine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Acts there is mention of <hi>Philip, Peter,</hi>
                     <pb n="240" facs="tcp:178475:131"/>
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Peter,</hi> who plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Gospell in <hi>Lyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> Chap. 9. 32. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted <hi>Cornelius</hi> a <hi>Gentile,</hi> Chap. 10. 1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Of <hi>Philip</hi> who plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the same in <hi>Samaria,</hi> which was by him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, Cha. 8. vers. 5, 6. and of <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn,</hi> who confirmed the plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Samaria,</hi> ver. 14. 17</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Of <hi>Paul,</hi> whose tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, troubles, cures and miracles are set downe from the 13. Chapter to the end of the booke; of whom wee may here say
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:178475:131"/> lesse, because there is so much of him in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Epistles hee wrote to seuerall Churches, as hereafter followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <head>THE EPISTLES.</head>
                  <p>AN Epistle is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar manner of deliuering &amp; sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying our minds to per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons absent: which were necessary in the time of the New Testament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Gospell was preached to all, but the law was cooped vp with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:178475:132"/> the wals of <hi>Iurie.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, many persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were vnder the Gospell, and not vnder the Law; and therefore was the holy Ghost cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Comforter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
                  <p>Of these Epistles, some were called Canonicall, or Catholicke, others not.</p>
                  <p>Epistles are called Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, either as writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the whole church, as the second Epistle of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and that of S. <hi>Iude;</hi> or else, in respect of doctrine necessary, to all Christians, and so the
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:178475:132"/> 1. Epistle of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; that of S. <hi>Iames</hi> is called Catholike. The other Epistles are directed to one Church or person, which the other are not, but <hi>Iohns</hi> two latter.</p>
                  <p>It was necessary the Apostles should write E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles, because their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie was oftentimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained, that they could not bee present in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</p>
                  <p>It was expedient that S. <hi>Paul</hi> should write ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Epistles.</p>
                  <p>First, because hee had done much hurt with his penne, and therefore
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:178475:133"/> should now labour to do good therewith.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as hee had an admirable gift in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, so hee imployeth the same to the glory of God, and benefit of his Church; in that hee suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered more then the rest of the Apostles, and wrote more. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. he is called the Apostle of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The number of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles written by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> were 14.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 To the <hi>Romanes,</hi> by them sometimes were vnderstood a great part of the world, otherwhile
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:178475:133"/> for whole <hi>Italy,</hi> whereof <hi>Rome</hi> is the chiefe Citie; and in this place (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) for the Citizens thereof, who were great boasters of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse by the Law.</p>
                  <p>To the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> a rich and famous Citie in <hi>Achaia,</hi> hauing it name from a man so called; the Inhabitants in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Epistle are noted for certaine vices, and in the second for obstinacy, &amp; incorrigeblenesse.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> To the <hi>Galatians,</hi> or Inhabitants of <hi>Galatia,</hi> part of <hi>Phrygia,</hi> in <hi>Asia</hi> the Lesse, that intermix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:178475:134"/> S. <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine with false doctrine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> To the <hi>Ephesians,</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned amōg the famous Cities of <hi>Asia,</hi> famous for <hi>Dianaes</hi> Temple, and for S. <hi>Pauls</hi> teaching in that Citie; the argument thereof is, To confirme them in the Doctrine that he had taught them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> To the <hi>Philippians,</hi> a City of <hi>Thracia,</hi> bearing name of that famous King of <hi>Macedon</hi> that built it; this people were ioyfull for the benefit of the Gospel by the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of S. <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> To the <hi>Colossians,</hi> a
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:178475:134"/> Town of <hi>Phrygia,</hi> where <hi>Archippus</hi> was Pastor: the argumēt, for the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment of their faith against corrupt teachers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> To the <hi>Thessalonians,</hi> a famous Citie of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia:</hi> The Citizens in the former Epistle are cōmended for their faith and obedience, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> and in the second, for their valor in suffering for the same. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>To <hi>Timothie,</hi> an Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelist, descended of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Parents, his father a Greeke, his mother a Iewesse, and hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe left as a Bishop at <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
                     <hi>Ephesus</hi> by S. <hi>Paul.</hi> In
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:178475:135"/> the former Epistle, <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> is incited and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to bring forth the fruits of good professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in the second, to constancy in suffering.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> To <hi>Titus,</hi> left at <hi>Creta</hi> as a Bishop by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> the argument, for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment of works well begun.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> To <hi>Philemon,</hi> a person very rich and highly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of, perswading him to mercy towards <hi>Onesimus</hi> a fugitiue ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> To the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> or <hi>Iewes,</hi> which were borne in <hi>Iurie,</hi> and for the most
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:178475:135"/> part dwelled there also, yet wrote in Greeke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that tongue was well knowne vnto them; The Argument, To di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish the Priesthood of Christ, from the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Romans" type="epistle">
                  <head>ROMANES.</head>
                  <p>HE that would bee a Citizen of Heauen, may be assured of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God, predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him thereunto, by the effects of his iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by faith, and san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the Spirit, moouing him to liue a godly and charitable life towards his brethren;
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:178475:136"/> without boasting of any thing in our selues, nor suffering our selues to be seduced by erroneous teachers; to which effect this Epistle directeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1 Corinthians" type="epistle">
                  <head>1. CORINTHIANS.</head>
                  <p>HEE that would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue faction in the Church, and vnnecessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contentions in Law, vncleannesse of body, or would bee rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed touching the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is directed in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle; where, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of things amisse in others, he that sinneth of
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:178475:136"/> ignorance or infirmitie may be infamous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and seducers confuted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2 Corinthians" type="epistle">
                  <head>2. CORINTHIANS.</head>
                  <p>WHerein wee may see, what godly persons (Ministers especially) do reape at the hands of the wicked, false Teachers, and others, for their loue to dragge their soules out of the puddle of sin, and snares of Satan.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Galatians" type="epistle">
                  <pb n="254" facs="tcp:178475:137"/>
                  <head>GALATIANS.</head>
                  <p>WHere wee may see the priori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue workes in the Act of Iustification; which precedēcy granted, faith and workes are hand-fasted, and doe necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concur in the practice of Christianitie, against such false Apostles as taught Circumcision, and Iustification by the workes of the Law.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Ephesians" type="epistle">
                  <pb n="255" facs="tcp:178475:137"/>
                  <head>EPHESIANS.</head>
                  <p>INtreating of the grace of God, in making of the Iewes and Gentiles one Church, Chapters 1, 2, 3. and shewing how Christians are differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from that they were by nature; and also dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in their generall and particular Callings, and prepared for the spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all combate in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters following.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Philippians" type="epistle">
                  <head>PHILIPPIANS.</head>
                  <p>IN which EPISTLE wee may plainely see, what good they doe
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:178475:138"/> get in spirituall things, that minister of their Temporals to the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities of Gods afflicted seruants, Ministers espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, by their prayers, praise, and good aduice; and that none should be offended at the Crosse, but bee emboldened by seeing their constancy in their sufferings, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the benefit that commeth thereby.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Colossians" type="epistle">
                  <head>COLOSSIANS.</head>
                  <p>FRom the Contents of this Epistle, a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may learne his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse in Christianity, in
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:178475:138"/> faith and knowledge of God, practice of good workes, &amp; thanksgiuing; so as heauen must be still his ayme, &amp; his thoughts raised vp thither.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1 Thessalonians" type="epistle">
                  <head>1. THESSALONIANS.</head>
                  <p>IF wee would be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted against the temptations of persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or would know how commendable it is for a Christian to suffer euill for good by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons neere vnto vs, wee are directed therein, Chapters 1, 2, 3. or would bee comforted in the death of our friends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:178475:139"/> the latter part of this Epistle sheweth it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2 Thessalonians" type="epistle">
                  <head>2. THESSALONIANS.</head>
                  <p>THAT persecutions and afflictions are the touchstone of the faith of Gods elect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that many shall fall away in the last time by the means of Antichrist, where, of him, and his pride and fall.</p>
                  <trailer>Hitherto of the Epistles directed to particular Churches: now of them to particular persons; such as were <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, Titus, Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="1 Timothy" type="epistle">
                  <pb n="259" facs="tcp:178475:139"/>
                  <head>1. TIMOTHY.</head>
                  <p>IN the first Chapter, is as it were a Beacon of mercy, set vp for all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant sinners, in the example of <hi>Paul,</hi> to auoid despaire; and teaching them afterwards how to spend their time in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liuing, Ministers espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, &amp; that by reading the Word, and wisely rebuking sinne, chap. 5. and admonishing al sorts and sexes of their duties, Chap. 2. 3. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2 Timothy" type="epistle">
                  <head>2. TIMOTHY.</head>
                  <p>COntaining an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to stedfastnes
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:178475:140"/> in grace, by fore-telling of back-sliding, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of the last times Necessary now for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Christian to learne, that hee may know how to beare afflictions and wrongs patiently, by the directions of Gods Word, with the benefits that will come thereby.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Titus" type="epistle">
                  <head>TITVS.</head>
                  <p>A Direction for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of either sexe, how to behaue thēselues accordingly, whether in priuate or publike place, and of the Minister espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that hee may bee
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:178475:140"/> so qualified by Gods Word, as to bee able to direct others therby, and conuince the Refractory</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Philemon" type="epistle">
                  <head>PHILEMON.</head>
                  <p>BY example of <hi>Paul</hi> so earnest for <hi>Onesimus</hi> a Conuert, we ought to shew mercy, where God hath done it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Hebrews" type="epistle">
                  <head>HEBREWES.</head>
                  <p>WHEREIH wee may see the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Gospel aboue <hi>Moses</hi> Law, with the Mediator between God and Man. Iesus Christ, according to his three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:178475:141"/> Office, of King, Priest, and Prophet; and then of exhortations to the whole Church, to the end of the Epistle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="James" type="epistle">
                  <head>IAMES.</head>
                  <p>VVHerein all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons are instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted how to ioyne good life, with good professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, faith &amp; good works; and to beware of euill language, and partiality, in preferring the wicked rich, aboue the godly poore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1 Peter" type="epistle">
                  <pb n="263" facs="tcp:178475:141"/>
                  <head>1. PETER.</head>
                  <p>IN this Epistle is set forth the Royalty of Christians, and that their liues ought to be sutable therevnto, in their loue to Christ and his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and then of their duties in their particular Callings.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2 Peter" type="epistle">
                  <head>2. PETER.</head>
                  <p>WHerein we are perswaded to maintaine the faith we haue, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease therein, and other graces, against Heretikes, Hypocrites, &amp; Atheists,
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:178475:142"/> which swarme in the last dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1 John" type="epistle">
                  <head>1. IOHN.</head>
                  <p>VVHerein, after that the Apostle hath shewed the nature of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and worldly loue, he sheweth the loue of Charitie that should bee in Christians: who as they confesse one Christ for their Sauiour; so should they manifest their loue to him, in his Image, that is, in our neighbour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2 John" type="epistle">
                  <pb n="265" facs="tcp:178475:142"/>
                  <head>2. IOHN.</head>
                  <p>VVHerein, they that are graced with outward Titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, should striue to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue it, by louing the Truth, and repressing Seducers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3 John" type="epistle">
                  <head>3. IOHN.</head>
                  <p>FIrst, wherein all men may know to what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment they belong, by their loue or hatred to good or euill.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Jude" type="epistle">
                  <pb n="266" facs="tcp:178475:143"/>
                  <head>IVDE.</head>
                  <p>VVHerein wee haue the satanical Impe vncased, who vnder the Maske of Religion, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Christian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, would foyle Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracie, and make way to his own sensuality and auarice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Revelation (Apocalypse)" type="book">
                  <head>REVELATION.</head>
                  <p>OR the discouerie of things present, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the seuerall Churches that were in <hi>Asia</hi> the lesse; and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:178475:143"/> concerning the Church, and the opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made against it by Satan, the Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, and the man of sinne: and the Churches victory ouer them; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this life, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally in the life to come.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>